<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some observations and annotations upon the Apologeticall narration, humbly submitted to the Honourable Houses of Parliament; the most reverend and learned Divines of the Assembly, and all the Protestant Churches here in this island, and abroad.</title>
            <author>Steuart, Adam.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E34_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21620</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871463</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871463</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123874</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 6:E34[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some observations and annotations upon the Apologeticall narration, humbly submitted to the Honourable Houses of Parliament; the most reverend and learned Divines of the Assembly, and all the Protestant Churches here in this island, and abroad.</title>
                  <author>Steuart, Adam.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Christopher Meredith, and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard at the sign of the Crane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: A.S., i.e. Adam Steuart.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: An apologeticall narration, humbly submitted to the honourable Houses of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary permission to print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Westminster Assembly (1643-1652) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apologeticall narration, humbly submitted to the honourable Houses of Parliament --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123874:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME OBSERVATIONS AND ANNOTATIONS Upon the <hi>Apologeticall Narration,</hi> Humbly ſubmitted to the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able HOUSES of PARLIAMENT; The moſt Reverend and Learned DIVINES OF THE ASSEMBLY, And all the <hi>Proteſtant Churches</hi> here in this Iſland, and abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſign of the Crane. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:123874:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123874:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Reverend, and Learned DIVINES, THE AUTHORS OF THE <hi>Apologeticall Narration.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend and dear Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE high eſteem I have ever had of your Perſons, and the great holineſſe of your lives (deſiring ever to be ſuch my ſelf, as I eſteem you to be, except onely in your particular opinions, wherein ye diſſent from all Proteſtant, yea, all Chriſtian Churches in this World) had almoſt hindered me, from the publiſhing of theſe Conſiderations upon your <hi>Apologeticall Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> eſteeming, That it was not for any particular man, ſuch as I am, to oppoſe himſelf to ſuch a number of grave Divines, of ſo great learning, and ſo apparent Pietie: But on the other part, conſidering, that you, as my ſelf, are but men, ſubject to humane frailtie, that ye know but in part, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
<pb facs="tcp:123874:3"/>may erre in part, I thought, that this, which is in queſtion betwixt you, and all the Churches in the Chriſtian World, might be a part of your aberration in part, and of that which we know in part; And upon this conſideration, eſteemed it no leſſe a part of my dutie, and Chriſtian libertie, as a man, to oppoſe my ſelf to five men, then for five men to oppoſe themſelves to the common opinion of five hundred thouſand, to ſo many learned, ſo many holy Divines, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, and thouſands for one of you, no wayes inferiour to the learnedſt, and beſt amongſt you; And not onely to particular men, and Divines, but to ſo many, yea and thoſe the moſt pure, and moſt Reformed Churches of the World, amongſt whom there have been found ſo many thouſands who have ſealed Chriſts Truth with the loſſe of their goods, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their bodies, by the exile of their Perſons, yea, with their deareſt blood, and lievs, who if they wrought not miracles, at the leaſt God declared his Almighty Power in working miracles about them, and upholding them; (Men of ſo great worth, that the world was not worthy of them: And howſoever theſe Motives be great, yet wrought they not ſo much upon me as this, That I am perſwaded in my conſcience, that your opinion of Independency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if it were admitted (pardon my expreſsion till I be better inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you, or ſome others) could not but prove the root of all ſort of Schiſme, and Hereſie, and conſequently the utter overthrow of Chriſts Univerſall Militant Church here upon Earth. Beſides all theſe conſiderations, I had many more, and amongſt the reſt, your hard expreſsions againſt them that love, and pity you, your apparent reſolution in deſiring a <hi>Toleration</hi> of your Religion, and conſequently of a Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from our Churches, which howſoever they have power to hinder you, yet condeſcend to be ſuppliants to you, that you will entertain union, and communion with them. I may adde
<pb facs="tcp:123874:3"/>to all theſe your undervaluing of the Parliaments great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours towards you; for ye know, Brethren, how they (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, and your former Separation from all other Christian Churches) having taken to heart your hard uſage in thoſe evill times ye ſpeak of, (howſoever in reſpect of your number ye be very few, yea hardly the hundreth part, yea not ſo much as one part of the Divines of this Kingdom, in reſpect of your Separation) invited you moſt lovingly to be Members of this preſent Aſſembly of the moſt learned, holy, and reverend Divines of both Kingdoms; whereof, had not they given you the capacity, ye had been altogether incapable: And not onely that, but alſo having reſolved to ſend two Divines from hence with their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners to <hi>Scotland,</hi> they honoured one of you with this high favour (the greateſt they could confer upon you at that time) and ſo in effect did honour you with the half of the honour, which belonged to all the Divines of the Kingdom; And yet notwithſtanding all theſe great teſtifications of ſo great, and tender affections towards you, ye five men, five Members of the Aſſembly, (by whoſe Counſell, and Inſtigation, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what Motives we know not) joyned your ſelves in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Combination,</hi> without the knowledge of either Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or Aſſembly, to draw up and publiſh unto the World an <hi>Apologeticall Narration,</hi> as ye terme it, containing in effect, (howſoever ye name it) a ſingular deſire of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from them, that ſo cheriſh you, with ſome unworthy Nick-names, ye put upon them, who ſtile you by no worſe names, then Brethren. By ſuch proceedings, what elſe have ye done, but erected an Aſſembly in the Aſſembly, a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Aſſembly in a publike Aſſembly, by private Authority againſt publike Authority, taking private Reſolutions againſt all publike Reſolutions, whatſoever might be concluded ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Parliament, or Aſſembly; and in one word, an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb facs="tcp:123874:4"/>to overthrow the Aſſembly? Theſe reaſons joyned together with ſundry others, made me to think more then I ſay, and to ſuſpect that ye would ſay more then ye ſay. And therefore, laying all particular affections aſide, I reſolved my ſelf to publiſh theſe following <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> and <hi>Annotations</hi> upon this your <hi>Apologeticall Narration;</hi> which truely I do not out of any ſpleen againſt you (God knows it) for never one of you, ever offended me; yea, I may ſay, that I love you all from my heart, and that in writing of this, my ſoul is, as it were, rent in two parts, my underſtanding carrying it one way, and my will another; Chriſts verity forcing the one, and your ſingular piety alluring the other: But I muſt conclude, That it is better to follow God then man, what ever he be, or may appear to be; and that the will, that is but a blinde facultie, muſt let it ſelf be led by the light of the underſtanding, which is the eye of the ſoul. And as I write not out of ſpleen, ſo may I atteſt him, who ſeeth all things, that I do it not to gain any mans affection, or favour, much leſſe in hope of any other worldly ends; and that if I did it to gain any mans love, or friendſhip, I am as much deſirous of yours, as any others: No ſuch ends moved me: But if I have any knowledge of my ſelf at this preſent, at the writing of this Anſwer (which yet I know is not ſuch as it ſhould be) I may ſay, That my main aym has been Gods glory, and the edification of weak Brethren, who may have been miſled by your moſt learned Diſcourſe; eſteeming, that during the reſt of my Pilgrimage, which cannot be long, having no other thing to do, I ſhall do well to do this, and ſo improve my Talent to his glory, the Edification of his Church, and the Salvation of my own Soul, and ſo I remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very loving Brother in Chriſt, <hi>A. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123874:4"/>
            <head>Some Generall CONSIDERATIONS Upon the <hi>Apologeticall Narration.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="consideration">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether in any Eccleſiaſticall or Politicall Aſſembly of the Chriſtian World, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in things are carried by plurality of voices, it be ordinary for any inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able number thereof, to joyn in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular combination among themſelves; and therein to take particular reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to publiſh them unto the world; and ſo to anticipate upon the reſolutions of the whole Aſſembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="consideration">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>Whether in taking ſuch reſolutions, they ſhould not conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolve themſelves to quit the Aſſembly, and to appear as Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? And if any man or men ſhould do ſo, either in this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or this Aſſembly; if a connivence at ſuch a matter ſhould not be reputed for an act of great favour, love, and extraordinary tender affection towards them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="consideration">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:123874:5"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>Whether ſuch an inconſiderable member, in ſo doing, may not be refuſed by the parties, as incompetent Judges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="consideration">
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether this</hi> Apologeticall Narration <hi>was neceſſary, when ye</hi> found the calumnies, miſtakes, miſapprehenſions of your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and miſts, that had gathered about you, or were rather caſt upon your perſons, in your abſence, begin by your preſence again, and the bleſſing of God upon you, to ſcatter and vaniſh, without ſpeaking a word for your ſelves or cauſe? <hi>And if the honour the Parliament ſhewed you, in calling you to be Members of the Aſſembly, was not ſufficient enough, to juſtifie your perſons from all ſort of asperſions and calumnies, without any Apology? Whether after the diſſipation of ſuch Clouds, and ſuch a juſtification, this Apology was rather neceſſary, then before, when ye were under the cloud, and not juſtified?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="consideration">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>Whether this your <hi>Apologeticall Narration,</hi> wherein ye blame all Proteſtant Churshes, as not having <hi>the power of godlineſſe, and the profeſſion thereof, with difference from carnall and formall Chriſtians, advanced and held forth among them,</hi> as among you, be ſeaſonable, when the Church of God and this Kingdom ſtand in need of their Brotherly Aſſiſtance; and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of that of the Scots (againſt whom it is commonly thought to be particularly intended) who at this very time ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable, according to their duty, hazard their Lives and Eſtates for Gods Church, all this Kingdom, and you alſo?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="consideration">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>Whether (as it is obſerved by ſundry men of learning, and as ye have noted your ſelves) ye ſhould not have done better, to have ſit down your opinions by way of Theſes, and ſo manifeſted unto us, wherein ye agree, or diſagree with us, or from us? the Browniſts, Anabaptists, and theſe whom ye pretend to hold the ſame Tenets with you, in old and new <hi>England,</hi> and the Netherlands, then in a Rhetoricall and Oratorius way, endeavour in the moſt part of your Book, to publiſh your great Sufferings, and extraordinary Piety, and ſo to move us all to compaſſion, and raviſh us into admiration, as if ye meant rather to perſwade, then to prove them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="consideration">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:123874:5"/>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>Many alſo are very deſirous to know, whether this <hi>Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Narration</hi> publiſhed by you five alone, be publiſhed in the name of you five alone, or of all thoſe alſo, or apart of thoſe, whom ye pretend to hold your Tenets? to the end we may know in what eſteem to have it. And if in the name of you five onely, the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Contrivers thereof; Whether ye five can arrogate a power unto your ſelves, to maintain theſe Tenets, as the conſtant opinion of all your Churches, having no generall Confeſſion of their Faith thereabout? If in the name of all the reſt, we deſire ye would ſhew your Commiſſion from all your Churches, by what authoritie ye do it? Or if ye do it without Commiſſion and Authoritie from them, if that be not to aſſume unto your ſelves a greater <hi>Authoritative power,</hi> then that ye call Presbyteriall? yea, then ever was the Epiſcopall?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="consideration">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>It were alſo not amiſſe ye ſhould declare, Whether ye deſire a Toleration for you five alone in your Religion, or for all the reſt? <hi>Item,</hi> If a Toleration in publike, in erecting of Churches apart? or to live quietly without troubling of the State? as for the last, appearingly, ye may have it unſought; but for the reſt, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is wiſe enough, and knoweth what is convenient for the Church of God and the State.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="consideration">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>And becauſe your whole draught of this Book tends evermore unto a <hi>Toleration,</hi> and conſequently unto ſome Separation; I would willingly know of you? What things are to be tolerated, or not tolerated in Religion? not in private perſons, but in Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciations? And particularly, when the whole Kingdom is joyned in one Religion? What ſort of new Conſociations of divers Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, it may in good conſcience tolerate and receive into it? <hi>Item,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what ground Churches may, in good conſcience, make Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from other Churches, that deſire <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Communion with them? Whether they that aym at a Toleration and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be not rather bound to tolerate ſome ſmall pretended defects, not approved by thoſe from whom they deſire to ſeparate themſelves; (and especially, when they that are ſo deſirous of Separation, are not preſſed to be Actors in any thing againſt their conſcience) then to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123874:6"/>ſeparate themſelves from a Church, that teſtifies a great deſire to reforme the defects, pretended to be in it? Whether it were not better for them, that aym at Toleration and Separation, to ſtay in the Church, and to joyn all their endeavours with their Brethren, to reforme abuſes, then by Separation to let the Church of God periſh in abuſes? Whether they do not better, that ſtay in the Church to reforme it, when it may be reformed, then who quit it, for fear to be deformed in it?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="annotations">
            <head>ANNOTATIONS Upon the INSCRIPTION Of this BOOK</head>
            <head type="sub">[An Apologeticall Narration.]</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Apologies preſuppoſe ſome Accuſation, which here appears none; or if it be intended, as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logeticall anſwer to what hath been written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Opinions; it comes very ſhort, weak, and ſlender, and no way ſatisfactory to their Arguments.</p>
            <p>Neither is it a meer Apologeticall Narration, but alſo a grievous Accuſation againſt all our Churches, as deſtitute of the power of godlineſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So it is a miſtake in the very Title of the Book, which is either untrue, or inadoequate to the ſubject whereof it treateth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Humbly ſubmitted]</hi> So humbly ſubmitted <hi>to the honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Houſes of Parliament,</hi> as if they ſubmit not themſelves to your deſires, in granting you a Toleration (for any thing I can ſee) ye ſeem no wayes minded to ſubmit your ſelves to theirs. It ſeems alſo very probable, That being Divines, ye ſhould rather firſt have conſulted with the Aſſembly of Divines, your Brethren, then ſo <hi>ex abrupto,</hi> gone to the Civill Magiſtrate,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123874:6"/>that arrogates not to himſelf, any directive power in matters of Religion: This ſhould have teſtified more Brotherly and Chriſtian Charitie, then here it does of politicall humilitie: And it is more convenient to the ſpirit and power of godlineſſe; that the ſpirit of Prophets, in ſuch matters, ſhould be ſubject unto Prophets, then unto the ſpirit of the Civill Magiſtrate; who, for this effect, hath convocate an Aſſembly of Prophets, and would not undertake it himſelf. So this is a ſubmiſſion, That this <hi>moſt juſt and ſevere Tribunall, and moſt Sacred refuge, and Aſylum of miſ-judged innocence,</hi> requireth not of you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[By Thomas Goodwin, &amp;c.]</hi> We have hereupon already expreſſed in the Epiſtle, and in our ſeventh obſervation, what many Learned and good men deſire, and what may be their judgement hereupon about you five.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 1. <hi>Now Members of the Aſſembly of Divines]</hi> and this alſo we have touched in our Epiſtle, and upon <hi>[humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.]</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="notes">
               <head>Notes upon the firſt Page.</head>
               <p>Sect. <hi>1.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r ears, &amp;c.</hi>] Here beginneth this Apologeticall Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which, from this unto the ninth Section, Page the fifth, hath little or nothing materiall, touching the queſtions in controverſie betwixt our Brethren and us: Onely it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth a Narration of their godly wayes, whereupon they have never been challenged by their Brethren, that ever I could hear of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[filled with exclamations]</hi> What can be theſe exclamations or exclamators, we know not, and therefore anſwers not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. <hi>And now, &amp;c.</hi>] It may ſeem very probable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men, 1. That it ſhould have been more ſeaſonable, <hi>To have made this appearance into publike light,</hi> before your entrance into the Aſſembly, then ſo many Moneths after. 2. Before your Brethren, in ſubmitting your ſpirit of Prophets unto that of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123874:7"/>the whole Aſſembly, then in this extraordinary way, unpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelled by any like unto it in the world. 3. To have ſought of them a Teſtimony, then after this way, to take it at your own hand, and give it unto your ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[lain under ſo dark a cloud]</hi> Ye avow hereafter, that it is vaniſhed away; ſo ye loſe your pains, in taking away a cloud, that is no more: See our fourth obſervation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[The Supreme Judicatory, ſevere Tribunall, the moſt Sacred Refuge, and Aſylum for miſtaken, and miſ-judged innocence.]</hi> The Parliament indeed is all this, in civill cauſes, but it pretends no <hi>directive power in matters of Religion, by teaching, or preaching, or judging of controverſies of Religion;</hi> nor any <hi>executive power, that is intrinſecall unto the Church,</hi> as in the Vocation, Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Suſpenſion of Miniſters, in Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures, in Excommunication, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are meerly ſpirituall; but onely an <hi>executive, coercitive, and externall power; which is not in, but about the Church, and for the Church,</hi> whereby it compelleth refractory men to obey the Church: And this authoritie belongs actually, and in effect, in <hi>actu exercito</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>&amp; jure in re,</hi> to true Chriſtian Magiſtrates; but to others po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentially, <hi>in actu ſignate,</hi> and <hi>jure in rem</hi> onely, till they become true Chriſtians. In vertue of this Authority, when Parties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be offended by the Church, or if the Church judge any thing amiſſe, he may command the Church to reviſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examine its judgement, and to reforme it, if it containeth any thing amiſſe. And in this ſenſe, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, refuſing an unjuſt and exorbitant power, that the Counſell gave to him, ſaid very wiſely; <hi>Vos in Eccleſſa, ego extra Eccleſiam Epiſcopus,</hi> For he was no Eccleſiaſticall Miniſter, Overſeer, or Controller, but Gods Miniſter in the State, for the weal of his Church in the State; which was not formally of the State, howſoever materially it was in the State: Wherefore if your meaning here be, That the Parliament ſhould judge of the queſtions in debate, betwixt you and your Brethren; ye go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliaments intention, which eſteeming it ſelf, to have no calling of God thereunto, very wiſely did convocate an Aſſembly of Divines to that effect: Neither beleeve I, that ye will grant unto it and the Aſſembly both, ſuch an authority;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123874:7"/>or if ye grant it, I doubt, if ye will ſubmit your ſelves unto it: And indeed, to grant them ſuch a power, were nothing elſe, but to joyn your ſelves with the Arminians, who granted it to the Civill Magiſtrate, when they thought to have had him for them; and afterwards repented themſelves, when they found him againſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. <hi>[The moſt, &amp;c.]</hi> To this Paragraph I have nothing to ſay, but that it is the judgement of many very judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and godly Divines, That a Paſtour is bound to ſtay with his Flock, ſo long as he is not preſſed to be an Actor in any thing againſt his conſcience; which many good men have done in this Kingdom, and in ſo doing upheld many others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. <hi>[Neither, &amp;c.]</hi> Here I note two things. 1. Ye call other Churches, your Neighbour Churches; if ſo, they are your ſiſter Churches; And then how is it, That ye will not admit all the Members of their Churches, unto your Communion, at the Table of the Lord? Will ye, or dare ye, communicate with them, or not? If ye dare, how dare ye not admit them all unto your Communion? If ye dare not, how can ye hold them for Brethren, with whom ye dare not eat or drink, at that ſpirituall Feaſt of Brotherly Love and Charity? 2. Ye tell us, That for fear of violence and perſecution, ye made choice of a voluntary exile. If this be ſaid to excuſe your departure, I have nothing to ſay; But if it be to blame them, that notwithſtanding all perſecution, remained in their ſtations, I remit the Reader to the third Section: onely I adde this, That they, who notwithſtanding their perſonall perſecutions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in their Stations, in confirming others, are no leſſe to be commended then ye: Neither is the Souldier leſſe valourous, that ſtandeth by his Colours, fighting conſtantly, and courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to death, then he that leaveth them, flying away, upon any imminent danger whatſoever, whatever his affection be unto the cauſe: And if they all had fled away, what might have become of the poor Church of God in this Kingdom? it might been, that ere now, <hi>Impius haec tam culta novalia miles haberet, Barbarus has ſegetes.</hi> Praiſed be God, that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him in his mercy to uphold thoſe men in theſe dangers, that they might be a means of upholding the Members of his Church
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123874:8"/>here. Yea, who knoweth, if in ſuch corrupt times, many things were not rather to have been tolerated, which then could not be amended, then their Stations to have been deſerted, ſo they had not been Actors in ill doing? Neither was the <hi>watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of thoſe <hi>times</hi> ſo great, but that many good men might enjoy, and enjoyed in effect the Ordinances of Chriſt. And howbeit it had been ſo; yet was it not neceſſary therefore to make a Schiſme, in quiting the Communion of all other Churches abroad. Many Divines hold alſo, That the Miniſter of Chriſt ought not to fly away for his <hi>perſonall perſecution,</hi> but for that onely <hi>of his flock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 3. <hi>[This being, &amp;c.]</hi> In this and the next Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ye ſeem to come to the queſtion in controverſie, <hi>viz.</hi> Unto Eccleſiaſticall Government; but it containeth nothing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bative of your opinion, but onely narrative of your <hi>enquiry,</hi> and holy proceedings therein; which ye willingly deſire to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, that it has been the moſt holy that could be found by <hi>fleſh and blood, in any juncture of time that may fall out,</hi> as want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no helps that could further it, and having no impediments that could hinder it. Your helps were firſt, Gods Word; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, The Diſcipline of the Reformed Churches; Thirdly, That of the Non-Conformiſts; Fourthly, That of <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> Fifthly, The example and preſident of the Shipwrack of the Browniſts; Sixthly, The reaſon ye had to be true to your conſciences. The impediments or hinderances ye could have, were, firſt worldly temptations; ſecondly, aymes; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, education; fourthly, engagement to other Churches, from which all ye were free. But this Enumeration is imperfect; for the grace of God which is the principall help, without which we can do nothing, is here omitted. But let us examine them all according to the order that ye have ſet them down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[We lookt upon the Word of Chriſt, as impartially, and unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicedly, as men made of fleſh and blood are like to do in any jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of time, that may fall out.]</hi> This is much: As for us Brethren, being but men made of fleſh and blood; we know that we know but in part; that we do but in part the good, we have power to do; for we have power to do more good
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123874:8"/>then we do, that we may omit much evill, that we do; that of both we know very little, in reſpect of that we know not, <hi>For the heart of man is deceitfull, and who can know it:</hi> And as for others, we know much leſſe then of our ſelves, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their hearts, temptations, ayms, intentions, or their ſins, repentance, backſlidings, their falls, or upriſing; but leaſt of all of men poſſible in <hi>junctures of time to come, that God can create;</hi> for what know ye or we, Brethren, what may be? And therefore, we dare not be ſo bold, as to compare our ſelves with others in time preſent; much leſſe with thoſe that be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>in junctures of time to come,</hi> in eſteeming our ſelves as good, or better, then they may be: And therefore, I eſteem that your compariſon proceedeth rather of fleſh and blood, then of the ſpirit of God. We wiſh indeed, we were the beſt of all men, but we eſteem not our ſelves the beſt; Oh, that we might be but in the number of good men. We wiſh, we could ſay as much as ye; but again, we dare not, being conſcious of our own infirmitie, that we are but fleſh and blood.</p>
               <p>But ye ſeem to prove it, by removing of hinderances, as firſt, <hi>Of Temptations of the place ye went unto, your condition and company, which left you as freely to be guided by Gods Word, as the Needle toucht with the Loadstone is in the compaſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this is an imperfect Enumeration of Temptations: It containeth onely ſome externall, and yet not all, as thoſe, that proceed from the Divell, and omit internall Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereof ye purge not your ſelves ſufficiently: But left that company you in ſuch a condition? Medied it ſelf no more in a buſineſſe of ſo great conſequence, in eſtabliſhing a new Government, to which it was to ſubmit it ſelf? Did it ſo let it ſelf be led by the noſe? Had it no more intereſt in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? It is too much: Onely I adde, it is one of the greateſt Temptations, that a man can fall into, to eſteem himſelf without Temptations; and that ſuch a man, in ſuch a caſe, ſhould not need to ſay, <hi>Lead us not into Temptation:</hi> And was this no Temptation, that ye went out of your Countrey with ſome miſcontentment in it; that ye found your ſelves ſo conſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ye might frame your Government to your preſent eſtate and condition, as was requiſite in ſuch a company; that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123874:9"/>ſhuning too much one extremitie, becauſe of your ſufferings, ye ſhould preſently run into the other. Neither was this extravagant power a ſmall temptation, <hi>Nunquam ſatis fida potentia, ubi uimia eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[<hi>We had</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>of all men, the greateſt reaſon to be true to our own conſciences in what we ſhould embrace.</hi>]</p>
               <p>This Brethren cannot be ſaid, without a high eſteem of your ſelves, and great undervaluing of others: Have not other men as good reaſon as ye, to be true unto their conſciences, ſince they are all bound under the pain of eternall condemnation to that duty? What greater reaſon then this, can ye have? Have not theſe (whom ye call Presbyterians) who were condemned to death, for that Diſcipline, ready to be executed, who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward were exiled into forraign Countreys, wherein they ended their lives; who were men of no leſſe learning, abilities, and holineſſe of life, then any of your profeſſion, had they not (I ſay) as great reaſon to be true to their conſciences, as ye can have?</p>
               <p>Afterward in this Paragraph ye remove all ayms and ends, that might make you byas. [<hi>We had</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>no new Common-Wealths to rear, &amp;c.</hi>] As much may all Schiſmaticks ſay; Neither can every man have new Common-wealths to rear; neither can theſe of <hi>New-England</hi> ſay ſo: And as for you five, your number was too ſmall; and howſoever, ye had not King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in your eye, yet had every one of you, one in his heart, to ſubdue: <hi>Tunc omnia jura renebis, cum poteris Rex eſſe tui: Hoc regnum ſibi quiſque dat:</hi> This is a Kingdom, which every man by Gods grace, may take and give to himſelf, without any materiall Arms, or Armies: And howbeit, ye have no State ends, nevertheleſſe, as ye have very many good men, ſo have ye very many good States-men among you, yea, more then thoſe that maintain Presbyterian Diſcipline in regard of your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: But what Republikes had the Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> to rear, or worldly Kingdoms to ſubdue more then ye?</p>
               <p>Your <hi>mould</hi> (of Church Government) <hi>will be coexiſtent</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>with the peace of any form of civill Government on earth</hi>] that may be true of yours; but not of ours; for it cannot comply with that of the Turks; and we confeſſe ingenuouſly,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123874:9"/>that for any thing we know, yours will comply a great deal more with State, and State ayms, then ever S. <hi>Peter,</hi> S. <hi>Paul,</hi> or we could do; howſoever, ours ſubmitteth it ſelf willingly to all ſort of juſt Government, that is of God. Neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth the Parliament any thing more of the Church of GOD.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, ye had <hi>No preferment or worldly reſpects to ſhape your opinions for</hi>]; yet praiſed be God, your Miniſters have no want, but as great abundance of worldly means, as any of your Brethren that ſtand for Presbyteriall Government. But what preferment or worldly reſpects, could <hi>Calvin</hi> or <hi>Beza</hi> have had, who for the puritie of Doctrine, and of Diſcipline, introduced this Presbyteriall Government, whereby both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and all they that ſhould thereafter profeſſe the Goſpel, were deprived of all hopes of future preferment, and worldly reſpects? What preferment or worldly reſpects could they have, that refuſed them, when they were offered unto them, and prefer'd death and perpetuall exile, before good fat Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks? We know King <hi>James</hi> his round anſwer, when ſome asked him, wherefore he preferred not good men to Biſhopricks in <hi>Scotland? The Divell an honeſt man</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>will accept them.</hi> And what greater preferment have they, who at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent travell to bring in Presbyteriall Government? Are they richer then before they were? Are they to be in greater places, then Miniſters of the Word? Truely I may ſay ſomething that I have ſeen: Some of them ſundry times, ſo exhauſted their ſickly bodies, with pains in this Cauſe, that ſundry times they loſt their health, and fell ſick; but for worldly profit and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, I never heard of it.</p>
               <p>How great a fortune made <hi>Calvin</hi> with it? Who as it is known, and faithfully related by thoſe who did write his life, ſundry times refuſed worldly means, in a very fair and honourable way offered unto him; and whoſe Inventory after his death, hardly could amount to 40 pounds?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We had</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>nothing elſe to do but ſimply and ſingly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how to worſhip God acceptably. Anſw.</hi> So much may many others ſay. But moſt truely, may as much be ſaid of our firſt Parents in Paradiſe, yet they gave themſelves ſome other thing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123874:10"/>to do: Beſides all this, ye are too peremptorious, ye five, to ſpeak in the name of all the reſt; for howſoever, every one of you, may anſwer for one, <hi>viz.</hi> for himſelf; yet can none of you, nor ye all; anſwer for all thoſe of your profeſſion, ſince their hearts are unknown to you, and ye have no warrant from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>We were not engaged by Education, &amp;c.</hi>] And yet it is a bleſſing of God, by Education to be engaged to good, and bred in a true Doctrine and Eccleſiaſticall Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: Neither eſteem I, that it was a curſe to the People of God, to have been bred in his Covenant: Neither think ye it, a curſe to yours, to have been bred amongſt you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye ſuppoſe that other Reformed Churches, might not ſee in all things:</hi> So ſuppoſe we of you, and that with greater reaſon, being but five men, not comparable with ſo many lights of the World, of whom ye make your ſelves judges.</p>
               <p>And yet ye eſteem wrong <hi>in eſteeming, that their intention was moſt ſpent in the Reformation of Doctrine.</hi> 1. For that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly to accuſe them of negligence, in reforming of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. 2. Becauſe their Conſultations, and Epiſtles, ſent to ſundry Churches abroad, teſtifies the contrary. 3. Becauſe the French tia vell very much about their Diſcipline, and have reformed ſundry things therein. 4 And have a great many more helps, then ye to frame it, to Gods Word; for it is expreſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, every Church Ruler, to read it diligently: Once every three moneths it is read in their Conſiſtory; and what ever any man findeth defectuous in it, is repreſented to the Synod wherein there are ſo many of the learnedſt, moſt judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and holy Divines of the whole Kingdom; by whom after due Examination, by Common-advice, in the fear of the Lord, at may much better be reformed, then by the advice of one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Miniſter, and two or three Ruling Elders in their particular Congregation: And to think that one of you, can ſee more, then ſo many learned and Godly men, gathered in the fear of the Lord, cannot be thought without too good opinion of your ſelves. 5. Beſides all this, a good Diſcipline, may very well be eſtabliſhed, by men of leſſe holineſſe of life, ſo be it, they have greater abilities, for the gift of conſtituting a good Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123874:10"/>is not a gift proper to a good man, but to a good Church Officer it is not <hi>Gratia grarum faciens, ſed gratis data;</hi> not a ſaving gift or grace that maketh us gracious or acceptable to God, but graciouſly given or beſtowed upon us; not to ſave our ſelves, but other men, as the gift of Propheſie; for a man in preaching and ruling, may ſave others, and damn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And a man may be a very good Prophet or Ruler in the Church, if he have the abilities thereunto, and exerciſe them well; and an ill man, if he let not himſelf be taught and ruled: So we may ſay, a man may be a good Citizen, a good King, a good Souldier, or a good Cobler, but an ill man.</p>
               <p>Ye grant, that <hi>In Doctrine they had a moſt happy hand:</hi> but wherefore may ye not judge them, as well to have had an happy hand in Diſcipline? Was Gods hand more deficient to them in the one, then in the other? Or had they leſſe abilities? Or uſed they not their abilities? What reaſon rather for the one, then for the other? Had they more Kingdoms to ſubdue then ye? Or any other politicall ayms? Or greater temptations then ye?</p>
               <p>In the ſame Paragraph, ye propound your Obtervations: <hi>viz. That that Government, viz. Presbyteriall hath been accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with more peace then yours;</hi> and it is very true, for who can tell, how many Schiſmes and Hereſies your Government is ſubject unto? What Diviſions and immortall hatreds it hath bred in <hi>New-England? &amp;c.</hi> 2. If it hath more peace, then it is ſuch, as it ſhould be, and obtaineth its adequate end, which is the externall peace of the Church.</p>
               <p>Ye adde, <hi>That the power of godlineſs had not bin advanced amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at in this Iſland.</hi> From whence ye ſeem to infer, that it is not ſo good as yours. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. As for your Antecedent; it is too bold to make your ſelves Judges of the power of godlineſſe in other Churches, and to judge your ſelves the holieſt of all others.</p>
               <p>But ye prove it by their own Confeſſion: <hi>Anſw.</hi> Brethren ye do not well to take advantage upon other mens Humilitie for to depreſſe them, and extoll your ſelves; They do well to think ſoberly of themſelves: So do not ye in eſteeming ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of your ſelves, and ſo meanly of them. 2. And the French are very courteous and civill, but the more courteous and civill they be, the more diſcourteous, and uncivill be ye, that take
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123874:11"/>advantage by their courteouſneſſe and civilitie, to depreſſe them under your ſelves. 3. They have alſo this defect, that they have too many complements: But they ſay alſo, <hi>Let compliments ne doibvent point eſtre pris au pied de la lettre,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements muſt not be taken literally. It ſeems ye have not much travelled amongſt them, or remarked well the faſhion of the Countrey.</p>
               <p>But put the caſe, your Antecedent were as true as it is falſe: yet your Conſequence is naught, becauſe of many captions and ſophiſtications it containeth; onely I will touch two, the firſt is <hi>fallacia non cauſae, ut cauſae,</hi> a fallacious argumentation which bringeth a falſe and apparent cauſe, for the true cauſe of the effect, or a falſe effect for the true effect of the cauſe; for if there were a greater power of godlineſſe amongſt you, then in other Churches, the cauſe thereof, ſhould not be the fault of the Government, but of the Divell, of thoſe that govern, or are governed; not becauſe your Diſcipline is better then ours, or ours worſe then yours; But 1. becauſe the Divell evermore aſſaults more the true Church, the true Doctrine, and true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, then the corrupted Church, her corrupted Doctrine or Diſcipline; to the end, that thereby he may calumniate them all, imputing craftily to the Church of God, to the true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline, that which ſhould be imputed to himſelf. Or 2. Becauſe that the Governours or Rulers of the Church, put not the Diſcipline duly in execution: Or 3. Becauſe they that ſhould be governed, will not obey the trueth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Put the caſe the Antecedent were true, and there were no ſuch captious argumentation: Yet from hence, ſhould it not follow that Independent, but that Epiſcopall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be better then the Presbyterian; becauſe the power of godlineſſe acknowledged by ſtrangers, to be greater here, then with them, was not in <hi>Holland,</hi> or in <hi>New-England,</hi> under Independency; but in old <hi>England,</hi> not under Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent (which hath never here been received) but dependent, <hi>viz.</hi> Epiſcopall Government, that could not endure Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but perſecuted it: So Brethren, here according to your faſhion, you prove that which ye intend leaſt to prove, wherein ordinarily ye are very unfortunate: And if this ye prove, it is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:123874:11"/>another Sophiſtication, commonly called <hi>fallacia ignorationis elenchi,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, when ye prove one queſtion or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion for another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye had</hi> (ſaid ye) <hi>the light of old Non-conformiſts, and their draughts of Diſcipline:</hi> But ye condemned all, as Soveraign Judges, <hi>And that much more commended to us, becauſe</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>they were our own:</hi> Here ye manifeſt a temptation, which ye concealed before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye had the fatall miſcarriages and ſhipwrack of thoſe of the Separation,</hi> whom ye ſay, we <hi>call Browniſts:</hi> But ſo call not ye them, becauſe ye ſymbolize more with them, and had rather call us Calvinians, with the Papiſt, then them Browniſts, with us, as they merit; becauſe of the Author of their Sect.</p>
               <p>Afterwards, in the laſt part of this Paragraph, ye come to the examples of <hi>New-England, improved</hi> (as ye ſay) <hi>to a better Edition, and greater refinement;</hi> whom ye extoll very highly, in comparing them with <hi>our father Abraham,</hi> and <hi>yet ye ſtood</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>as unengaged Spectators.</hi> So then your Religion in this point was in <hi>abſtractione praeciſionis,</hi> abſtracted and ſeparated from all Religion, without all Religion, and to live as Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: This your Religion in this point, was very ſpeculative, and if it were in any other matter then that of Religion, we might juſtly ſay, <hi>Spectatum admiſſi riſum teneatis amici.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We reſolved not</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>to take up our Religion, by, or from any part.</hi> Neither could ye, being ſo abſtract from all parties, for ye diſſented from all the World; ye held all the World for parties, and made your ſelves Judges of all the World, till ye had made choice of your new Religion: If this Method in making choice of Religion, be good and honeſt, then all thoſe that are bred in your Religion, ſhould do ſo; which as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, ye will no wayes grant.</p>
               <p>Upon this Section, wherein ye ſo much extoll your <hi>New-England</hi>-men, I muſt ſay ſomething of thoſe that ſtood for Presbyterian Government: And not to inſiſt upon this, how ſome of them, as the Hiſtories relate, had the gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie? What miracles, or at leaſt, marvellous things, were done by, or about them, in the time of their Impriſonment, and afterwards, in their Exile for that Cauſe: How God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123874:12"/>poured forth his Judgements upon thoſe that were inſtruments of their vexation; and afterward, extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily delivered them, upon their repentance: How ſome of them, in ſtrange Countries, extraordinarily got the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Countrey in three moneths, ſo as to be able to Preach: How the people flockt about them in their houſes: How powerfully they preached twice a day; which was thought inſupportable to humane nature, in reſpect of <hi>the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of their action;</hi> and that not for one day, but all the dayes of their lives, to the admiration of many thouſands: How the Papiſts themſelves (howſoever ordinarily in their ſpeeches they condemned all <hi>Huguenots</hi> to hell) yet excepted them, becauſe of the holineſſe of their lives: How they were never out of Prayers, Meditation or Preaching, as ſundry eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes here can teſtifie: How all the Prieſts and Doctors, even the learnedſt of them, that were ſent to the place where they were, to hinder the converſion of the Papiſts, were converted themſelves: Onely I will ſay one word of ſome, who, not above four or five years ago, undertook a Voyage for a new Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>America,</hi> in as great a Wilderneſſe, as any of your <hi>New-England</hi>-men, and that with far leſſe worldly means, onely for Gods Service; Theſe men, I ſay, being about the number of one hundred and twenty in one Bottom, and ſome thouſands of miles on their way, it pleaſed God that a Tempeſt ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſeized them, as in it they loſt their Rudder, ſpent all their Maſts ſave one, and ſprung three Leaks, whereby the water came in in ſuch aboundance, that, notwithſtanding their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary diligence at the Pumps, as alſo their indefatigable pains in lading it out by Buckets, hardly could they ſave the Ship from ſinking under them: And yet in this caſe, ever ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping againſt hope, the Tempeſt continuing, it pleaſed him, who commands the Windes and Tempeſts, by the ſame Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt to bring them back to the very Port they ſet out of, and after wards made them Judges of thoſe that had unjuſtly judged them; and inſtruments, with the reſt of the Kingdom, for the eſtabliſhing of the Presbyteriall Government in greater purity there, from whence it was almoſt caſt out. What theſe mens lives were, the world can with no leſſe admiration wonder at,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123874:12"/>then at their wondrous deliverance. And yet for all this, will I not compare <hi>theſe men with any men in the World, in any jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of time, that may fall out.</hi> As I honour their gifts, ſo do I other mens alſo; but which of them all, be the beſt men, or moſt impartiall Judges, he knoweth beſt, who knows the hearts of all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. In this Section, ye give out your judgement of other Churches; and in the next, <hi>viz.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. other Churches judgement of you: I beleeve ye underſtand thoſe of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ye acknowledge the Churches under Epiſcopall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>England,</hi> and under Presbyteriall in <hi>France, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> for true Churches, and their Miniſtery, for a true Miniſtery.</p>
               <p>But here I deſire, with many others, to know what ye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by true Churches, and a true Miniſtery? Whether a <hi>Metaphyſicall, Logicall, or a Morall veritie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ye underſtand that they be true Churches, <hi>Veritate Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſica Entis &amp; Tranſcendentali,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Dú Pleſſis,</hi> and many of our Divines grant unto the Romiſh Church; <hi>viz.</hi> That ſhe is a true Church, (as a Pocky whore, is a true Woman) how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever her fleſh be ſo conſumed with corruption, that ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live, but muſt die of it, and that none can touch her, without danger of being infected with her ſickneſſe; for ſhe is an Harlot and a Whore, howſoever clothed with Scarlet: We thank you for your favour: Ye hold us in the ſame Categorie with <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ye hold us a true Church, <hi>veritate logica, and morally,</hi> for a pure Church; wherefore deſire ye a Toleration? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will ye not joyn with us, and communicate, as Brethren, with us?</p>
               <p>But ye adde a little after the middle part of this Section, <hi>That ye both did, and would hold, a Communion, with all thoſe Churches, as with the Churches of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what communion is this, ye hold with theſe, rather then with Papiſts, Browniſts, Anabaptiſts in <hi>England,</hi> and the Lutherans?</p>
               <p>If ye ſay in Doctrine; that Union is not externall, ſince ye
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123874:13"/>teſtifie it not, by your externall Communion in the Sacraments with us; for ye will not admit all thoſe to your Communion, that we admit to ours: 2. Neither will thoſe of <hi>New-England,</hi> whom ye cry up, and extoll ſo highly, admit thoſe of our Church to their Communion, or to be Members of their Churches, unleſſe of late, they have changed their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ye, and they temporize in conforming your opinions to the times, and commenſurate them to Politicall ayms for Toleration. 3. Neither know we, whether they will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with us; at leaſt their Writings and Letters, from <hi>New-England,</hi> which heretofore we have ſeen, teſtifie no ſuch thing; ſo that in this ye diſſent from them, unleſſe they within this yeer, diſſent from themſelves. 4. By the ſame reaſon, ye may communicate with Schiſmaticks, and men that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated amongſt your ſelves for their ill life, <hi>viz.</hi> drunkards, blaſphemous perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 5. By the ſame reaſon ye communicate with ſome Papiſts in profeſſion, that beleeve all that we beleeve in Doctrine; 6. And with them all, and all Hereticks in part, becauſe they agree in part, in the Doctrine, with us.</p>
               <p>If it be replied, That they with whom they communicate, muſt alſo be of good life; I duply, then it is not a meer <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in Doctrine,</hi> but in ſome other thing beſide, <hi>viz.</hi> In <hi>good life.</hi> And then 2. If they have both ſound Doctrine, and be of a good life; or have Faith, which cauſes good Doctrine, and Charitie the cauſe of a good life: Wherefore deſire ye a Toleration, to make a Sect apart, or what deſire ye more, to make up one Church with them?</p>
               <p>But howſoever ye pretend this reall Profeſſion of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us, yet ye overthrow it by your reſtriction after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>viz. To ſuch as ye know to be Godly, that came to viſit you in your exile:</hi> But ye will not admit all the Members of our Churches, but ſuch as ye onely judge, not we, to be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our Church.</p>
               <p>Ye ſay in the ſame Section, <hi>That ye Baptize your Children in our Pariſhionell Congregations:</hi> Wherefore then will ye not as well communicate at the Lords Table with us all? And if ſo, Wherefore will ye not likewiſe admit us all to your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion?</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:123874:13"/>
               <p>In the 8. §. <hi>[And as we alwayes, &amp;c.]</hi> In this Paragraph, or Section, ye ſhew the judgement of forraign Churches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning you, how <hi>ye both mutually gave, and received the right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ds of fellowſhip:</hi> How they gave you Churches to Preach in, ſome Priviledges, <hi>a maintenance annually for your Miniſters, &amp;c.</hi>] So here in <hi>England</hi> hitherto ye have had libertie to Preach in our Churches, and may have, if ye will, and ſome of you have ſome Benefices: But if ye go on, ayming at a Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and conſequentlie, at ſome Separation, as we have ſhewed, I doubt if ye ſhall, or ſhould have any annuall allowance at all, or Churches to Preach in, as before you had. Moreover, we know not, upon what grounds ye were tolerated in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands;</hi> whether it was not in conſideration of your precedent afflictions, hoping that ye might ſubmit your ſelves to Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Government in your own Countrey, if it were well eſtabliſht; or in favour of ſome Merchants; by publike or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate authoritie, Eccleſiaſticall or Civill, or other wayes. Onely we ſay, That many Sects are tolerated there: Neither how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit ye were tolerated in the <hi>Netherlands, Polonia</hi> or <hi>Germany.</hi> where many Religions are tolerated and permitted out of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill reſpects, Is it equitable, ye ſhould be tolerated here, where there is one onely Religion profeſſed, and one Goverment, as we ſhall ſee hereafter.</p>
               <p>In the 9.10.11.12.13.14. ye give account of your Practices in publike Worſhip, Church Officers, matter of Government and Cenſures, and your directive principles in all this: Hence in the 15.16.17.18.19.20.21. ye infer your Concluſion of Independencie of every particular Congregation. As for the parts of your publike worſhip, we conſent with you.</p>
               <p>In your Church Officers, ye acknowledge with us four; <hi>viz. Paſtours, Teachers, Ruling Elders, and Deacons.</hi> But ye laſh us a little with your Parentheſis about our Ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. <hi>[With us not Lay, but Eccleſiaſtique perſons, ſeparated to that ſervice.]</hi> Here ye ſeem to accuſe the Reformed Churches in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands, Scotland, &amp;c.</hi> as if they all eſteemed them Lay, and not Eccleſiaſticall Perſons. If this be your minde, it is a great miſtake in you; and we can produce their writings to the contrarie; if not, we know not, to what
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123874:14"/>end, ye inſerted this particular Parentheſis. As ye therefore inſerted yours, ſo do we ours <hi>[but not Preachers, or Teachers of the Word:]</hi> And therefore we deſire to know of you, if Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders have power to teach; as it is maintained by other Independents; and if they Preach or Teach, how they can be diſtinguiſhed from Preachers, and Teachers? For all Charges receive their unitie, and diſtinction from their Acts, and Ends: Wherefore, if the Ruling Elder Preach, or Teach, which is the Act, and End of the Preacher, and Teacher, he muſt have the ſame Office with Preachers, and Teachers. 2. The Apoſtle alſo diſtinguiſhes them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Wherefore then confound ye them?</p>
               <p>Ye adde in this 9. Section concerning <hi>Excommunication upon obſtinacy and impenitency,</hi> this Parentheſis, as worthy of ſome particular obſervation, <hi>[which we bleſſe God we never uſed]</hi> as if your Churches were ſo pure, that not one man ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it: We cannot ſay ſo much of our Churches: Neither can your Brethren of <hi>New-England</hi> ſay ſo much of theirs: We know, that ſome have been Independenters, as we our ſelves have heard from their own mouthes, that now are become Anabaptiſts: And whether ſuch men merited it, or not, judge ye: If they merited it, ye have been very partiall, and unjuſt, in not uſing of it: So that proceeds not from want of demerits, in the perſons to be puniſhed, but of juſtice in the Rulers to execute it.</p>
               <p>Neither do we deny, but a number of very holy perſons may be gathered together, who may ſo carrie themſelves for ſome time, as not to commit any great offence with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacie, to deſerve Excommunication, if the choice be good. But to ſay, that it may laſt long ſo in Populous Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and in a great number of Churches, ye may tell us this news, when your Churches are multiplied, and become as Populous, and have endured as long as ours. We could tell wonders alſo of our Churches in ſome parts, in the beginning of the Reformation: But the queſtion is not, who liveth, holieſt, but whoſe Diſcipline is moſt conform unto Gods Word?</p>
               <p>Your Directive Principles were three. 1. <hi>Gods Word,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123874:14"/>and the Law of Nature fully known.</hi> 2. <hi>Not to make your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent judgement, and practiſe a binding Law unto your ſelves, for the future.</hi> 3. <hi>In matters of greateſt moment, and controverſie, ye ſtill thoſed to practiſe ſafely, and ſo as ye had reaſon to judge, that all ſorts, or moſt of all the Churches did acknowledge warrantable, although they make additaments thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We agree with you in theſe principles in generall;<note place="margin">§ 11. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</note> and nevertheleſſe we muſt touch a word in paſſing, of that, which we obſerve in every one of them, and in every Paragraph. And firſt, in the 11. §. about the midſt thereof, where ye ſay, That in Gods Word <hi>ye found Principles enough, not onely fundament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and eſſentiall to the being of a Church, but ſuperſtructory alſo to the welbeing of it, and thoſe to you clear and certain.</hi> We know not what ye call Fundamentall, and Eſſentiall, unto a Church; for the Eſſences of things are unknown unto us; Yea, the moſt part of the Philoſophers themſelves, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about Eſſences, confeſſe, that we know the Eſſence of nothing, but that onely of man, which they ſay is <hi>animal ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionale;</hi> and yet, in this they diſſent, and many ſay, that this is but an accidentall expreſſion of his Being: If ye cannot then declare us the Fundament, and Eſſence of the Church, ye are barbarous to us, and ſpeak in a Language, as unknown to us, as unto your ſelves.</p>
               <p>Again, we deſire to know, What ye underſtand here, by the Being of a Church: whether her internall, or externall Being? In Doctrine and Holineſſe? or in Diſcipline? If the firſt, it is not to the purpoſe; for we have no Diſpute here with you about the internall Being, or Doctrine of the Church, as ye confeſſe your ſelves, but about her externall Being, or Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: And in this alſo we confeſſe our ignorance, that we know not wherein conſiſteth its Eſſence or Being; and that we cannot diſtinguiſh it well from its Accidents, or Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructories, till ye teach us; and therefore deſire you to avoyd thoſe obſcure terms, and to give it us in ſome cleerer.</p>
               <p>Ye adde, That they <hi>will ſerve to preſerve your Churches in peace:</hi> whereof ye were not content, <hi>Sect.</hi> 6, ſaying, That howſoever Presbyteriall Government obtained this end, yet it differenced them not from carnall Chriſtians.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:123874:15"/>
               <p>In your third Directory Principle, <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. ye go very ſubtillie to work, by Metaphyſicall Abſtractions, as Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, in abſtracting their Genericall degrees of Eſſences from the ſpeciall; and their Specificall from their Individuall: For ye take ſome thing, wherein we all conſent; but not all, to the end there may be ſomething, wherein ye diſſent from us all. And ſo did the Arminians in their Confeſſion of Faith, wherein they abſtracted a degree of conſent, amongſt the moſt part of Chriſtians, yea with the Socinians, who deny the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and the Incarnation of the Son of God; and left that, wherein they diſſented, as indifferent.</p>
               <p>But this cannot hold; For howſoever, that, wherein, ye agree with us, be ſafe; yet is not that ſo <hi>ſafe,</hi> wherein ye diſſent from us all. Neither is it ſafe for ſo few men to diſſent From all the World, unleſſe they have very ſtrong reaſons for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and principallie, when the point wherein they diſſent, is not of great importance: For the leſſe it is, the greater is the Schiſme.</p>
               <p>Beſides this in this Directory Principle, howſoever ye ſeem to defer, and attribute very much to all Churches, in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their common Practiſes; yet ye give them nothing at all; for ye ſubmit their judgement to your own; and whatſoever, they hold commonly againſt you, ye call it an <hi>Additament;</hi> ſo that ye are not ready in any thing to aſſent with them, unleſſe they firſt aſſent unto you, which is a very prudent, and ſubtle Principle, as well to direct them by you, as you by them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Principle alſo cannot hold. 1. For in vertue thereof, ye have as well Union and Communion with Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Arrians, Anabaptiſts, Papiſts, Jeſuites, and other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, as with us; (howbeit not ſo much) for ye conſent with them all, in ſome common Principles, as with us: And ſo, as for your diſſent in particular Principles from them, ye may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate and do ſeparate your ſelves in effect from them; ſo muſt ye do from us, unleſſe ye ſhew us ſome other reaſon of Externall Union, and Separation, then yet you do.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:123874:15"/>
               <p>Before I quit this Paragraph, or Section, I muſt pray the Reader to note your ſubtle way of diſputing, how ye chuſe ſome things, wherein you, and we agree, calling the teſt Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments; to the end ye may not be bound to prove any thing. But this ſubtiltie is ſowed but with white thred, ſo as it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlie appears to all men, and will ſerve you for nothing. 1. For either theſe Additaments are conform, or repugnant to Gods Word, or indifferent? If conform, wherefore reject ye them? If repugnant, ye are bound to prove it by the Word, how they are condemned by it? If indifferent, ye have no reaſon to condemn them, or for them, to be ſuch eager Suitors for a Toleration of a contrary practiſe. 2. <hi>Item,</hi> If that which we have more then theſe common Principles, be an Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament, what be thoſe, that ye hold inſtead of them? For ye remain not within the Limits of bare Abſtractions, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions, but proceed farther to ſome particular Poſitive Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in your practiſe, for every Negation is founded in ſome Affirmation, and ſin is not a meer Negation of good; but alſo includeth ſomething, Poſitivelie contrary to good, either Phyſically or Morally, Really, or by reaſon.</p>
               <p>§ 14. <hi>p.</hi> 11. Ye bring ſome Inſtances of this Principle; 1. <hi>About the qualification of the Members of the Church, and promiſcuous receiving of good and bad:</hi> And ſay, That ye chuſe the better part, <hi>viz.</hi> the good, and not the bad; which ye ſuppoſe to be the practiſe of all Proteſtant Churches: So ye muſt judge all Infants, born in the Church, and admitted to Baptiſm amongſt you, to be good, and to have ſome portion of Chriſt, before they have the uſe of reaſon to know Chriſt; and ſo to be regenerate, when they are generated, or to conſort your ſelves with the Anabaptiſts here in <hi>England,</hi> in excluding Children from Baptiſm, till they have the uſe of reaſon, and profeſſe Faith; for in Independencie, and all other things, they agree with you, as they themſelves avow. But of this queſtion, about the Members of the Church, we ſhall, God willing, hear more hereafter, in a particular queſtion.</p>
               <p>Ten lines after, ye ſay, <hi>That the Rules, which ye gave up your judgements unto, to judge thoſe ye received in amongſt you by,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123874:16"/>were of that Latitude, as would take in any Member of Chriſt, the meaneſt, in whom there may be ſuppoſed to be the leaſt of Chriſt, Pag.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
               <p>If this be underſtood, of the receiving of men to the Church, abſolutely; or of their firſt entry therein, we have anſwered already; and by the grace of God, ſhall anſwer more hereafter: If of the reception of them, to the Lords Table; I anſwer, That the true Reformed Churches in <hi>Scotland, France,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands, &amp;c.</hi> receive no man to the Lords Table, whom they judge to be prophane, or ſcandalous, none but ſuch, as give an accompt of their Faith, and teſtifie it by externall Confeſſion, and Profeſſion in Doctrine, and Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: If any Preacher, or the Conſiſtory of Ruling Elders do other wayes, it is not by rule, or their ordinary practiſe, but through their negligence, which, when it is known, is condemned by all. We wiſh, that none come to the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts Body, amongſt us, but ſuch, as have, and feel ſome meaſure of Chriſt in themſelves: But who hath this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Chriſt; It is hard for any mortall man to know it, but he onely that hath it: It is likewiſe hard to know, what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Grace is requiſite, to make up a member of Chriſt, or of his Church. Some of the Caſuiſts, eſteem, that it ſufficeth a Roman Catholike, <hi>explicite</hi> (as they call it,) expreſly, cleerly, and plainlie, to beleeve this onely Article, <hi>I beleeve, what the Church beleeveth:</hi> Others eſteem it not enough, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adde this Article: <hi>I beleeve alſo, That the Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre:</hi> Others think this yet not enough, for they wiſh Chriſtians to beleeve this one more, <hi>viz. I beleeve there is a God.</hi> Some adde one more, <hi>viz. That they muſt beleeve Gods Providence, &amp;c.</hi> We beleeve, that men are bound to beleeve all Divine Truths, revealed in Scripture, as neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and to beleeve them by a juſtifying Faith: But what be theſe, that be abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation: What are theſe <hi>Fundamentalia, Eſſentialia,</hi> and <hi>Superſtructories:</hi> How may they be diſtinguiſhed one from another? What is <hi>maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum quod ſic,</hi> and <hi>minimum quod non:</hi> Or <hi>minimum quod ſic &amp; maximum quod non?</hi> Or your leaſt of Chriſt, whereupon a man may be admitted to be a Member of Chriſt, we cannot
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:123874:16"/>define it: We leave the Deciſion to more ſubtle Spirits, and to our Brethren, who uſe thoſe termes, and who, upon this <hi>minimum quod ſic,</hi> or <hi>leaſt bit of Chriſt,</hi> do found the Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſts Members into the Church. We eſteem their Diſputes too ſubtle, in the practiſe of Chriſtianitie, in judging others: And wiſh with the Apoſtle rather, every man to examine and try himſelf; For this <hi>directive Principle,</hi> we eſteem ſurer then that of our Brethren. We eſteem that ſuch a Confeſſion of Faith, and deſire of Communion, as ordinarily is profeſſed by them, who are admitted in Proteſtant Churches, may ſuffice.</p>
               <p>Here in the ſecond Inſtance of ſet Forme of Prayers, our Brethren note with a Parentheſis, that they condemn not others, who approve ſet Formes of Prayers <hi>preſcribed,</hi> and the <hi>Liturgis:</hi> But whether theſe of <hi>New-England,</hi> and others of their Profeſſion will not condemn them in this, we know not. I wiſh that this were not added rather in a compliance with the preſent time, then otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> They tell us, That the <hi>framing of Prayers, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons out of their own Gifts, are the Fruits of Chriſts Aſcenſion.</hi> But why not alſo of his death, and Reſurrection? Since he did merit this by his death.</p>
               <p>In their third Inſtance about Government, and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Diſcipline, we care not, what they ſay. The practiſe of the Orthodox Churches is this: They have divers Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Senats, or Courts, wherein ſome are coordinate, and others ſubordinated one to another. The loweeſt is their Conſiſtory, or Seſſion of the Paſtours, and the Ruling Elders, in one Pariſh Church: Then they have their Claſſes, which ſome call Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loques, others Presbyteries, made of all the Preachers of all the Pariſh Churches, belonging to ſuch Colloques, every one of them, accompanied with one Elder of his Church. 3. Their Provinciall Synods, made up of all the Miniſters of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, accompanied every one of them with one or two ruling Elders. 4. The Nationall Synod, compounded of a certain number of Miniſters, and Ruling Elders, according to the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of time, place, and other occaſions, and circumſtances, Delegate from all the Provinces, or Provinciall Synods. In the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123874:17"/>Conſiſtory, or Senate of the Pariſh Church they judge onely of things that be proper unto it, and of leſſe importance; that have no great difficultie. In the Colloque, of that, which is common to all the Churches of that Colloque; and of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of greater importance, that cannot be judged, or well determined in a Pariſh Church. In a Provinciall Synod, of that, which is common to all the Churches of the Province, &amp; other things of great importance, and all caſes, that cannot ſo ſoundly, or ſo ſurely be determined in the former Aſſemblies. In a Nationall, of that, which is common to all the Churches of the whole Kingdom; and others, that cannot be determined in the precedent Aſſemblies, as of matters of Appeal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> From the firſt, if any of the Parties finde themſelves grieved by its judgement, they may appeal to the ſecond, as from the ſecond, to the third, and from the third to the fourth. And all theſe Judgements and Proceedings are without money, charges, pecuniarie mulcts, or fines. And as their ayms are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, ſo be their puniſhments that they inflict upon their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents. Their puniſhments are cenſures, Suſpenſion from the Lords Table, and their greater Excommunication, which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily are never inflicted upon whole Churches, as our Brethren unjuſtly would challenge us, but on particular Perſons: If they had read the Diſcipline of the <hi>Scots, French, Netherlands.</hi> and other Reformed Churches, they needed not here have troubled themſelves and us with ſo many miſtakes: Or if they have read them, they deal not fairly with us. In ſome Churches, particular, or Parochiall Senates, or Conſiſtories, have power to ſuſpend from their Communion thoſe that be Members thereof; yea alſo to Excommunicate them, (from the which ſentence nevertheleſſe they may appeal unto the Superiour Senate or Judicatorie) and that for ſome particular reaſons.</p>
               <p>But this queſtion, God willing, we ſhall hereafter more fully diſcuſſe. Onely I note in paſſing, that our Brethren, Firſt, are here too ſparing of Titles to ſome, and too liberall to others: They name <hi>Cartwright,</hi> onely <hi>Cartwright,</hi> but <hi>Baynes,</hi> holy <hi>Baynes,</hi> in the ſame line, as if they would Canonize the one, making him Saint <hi>Baynes,</hi> (which we condemn in the Pope) and eſteem the other prophane, or of the vulgar, and dregs of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123874:17"/>Divines, which, as it is ſaid with reverence and reſpect of the one, ſo it cannot be ſaid, without diſparagement of the other. As for the diſtinction of <hi>Eccleſiae, in Primas, &amp; Ortas,</hi> it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a particular Queſtion apart.</p>
               <p>They ſay, 1. <hi>Every Church hath a full and entire power compleat within it ſelf, till it ſhould be challenged to erre groſly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. § 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Either by a compleat Power ye underſtand a Power abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely compleat, or in its own kinde or ſort: If ye under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the firſt, it muſt be Independent, for if it depend upon a Superiour to rectifie it, whereunto it muſt give an account of its judgement, and ſubmit it ſelf; in that regard, it is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, full, or entire. If of a Power compleat in its own kinde or nature, ye ſay nothing, but what we ſay, ſince it is our opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That every Particular Congregation hath a compleat Power in it ſelf, ſuch as is due to ſuch a Congregation, depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent upon that of Claſſes, and Synods (in caſe of Appeal) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may be challenged to erre groſly: If it be ſo, Wherefore conteſt ye with us, who give you no ſubject of quarrell, as not diſſenting from you in that particular?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, they ſay, That they <hi>claim not an independent power in every Congregation, to give an account, or to be ſubject to no others. Anſw.</hi> Then your power is dependent upon ſome others; then it muſt give an account, and be ſubject to ſome other: If ſubject to ſome others, then that other is ſuperiour; And what ſay we more? onely we ſay that there is a ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt ſuperiour and inferiour Eccleſiaſtical Judicatories, which ye hold here to be <hi>juris divini;</hi> we, <hi>partim divini, partim naturalis aut mixti.</hi> I pray you, Brethren, agree theſe two Propoſitions, how a Church can have a full and compleat Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and yet not independent; it ſhould ſeem to me, that either you contradict not us, or contradict your ſelves within the compaſſe of two lines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, they deny, That <hi>by the Inſtitution of Christ, or his Apoſtles, the Combination of the Elders of many Churches ſhould be the firſt, compleat, and entire ſeat of Church-power, over each Church ſo combined.</hi> Here ye attribute unto our Churches an opinion, That they own not as their own; <hi>viz.</hi> That the Combination of Elders of many Churches is the firſt Seat of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:123874:18"/>Church-power; for they hold the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That the firſt Seat of Government is in Parochiall Churches, ſince there the parties debates their cauſe, in firſt Inſtances; if ye ſay that by firſt, ye underſtand the principall; then ye cannot deny, but that Senate or Aſſembly, whereunto Particular Congregations are ſubject, whoſe judgement, according to Gods Word, they muſt obey, and of whoſe judgement their judgements de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, muſt be the principall Seat of Church-power; for that is principall, whereof the other dependeth, and to which the other is ſubject.</p>
               <p>Neither ſay we, That it is the compleat, and entire Seat of all Eccleſiaſticall Judgement; ſince in things of leſſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that onely belong to Particular Congregations, we hold the Elderſhip of that Congregation may judge, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times judges in effect compleatly, and entirely.</p>
               <p>But ye propound a tacite Objection: The Elderſhip ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined <hi>cannot challenge authority over the Churches they feed not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. We have anſwer'd, That our Elderſhip challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſuch authority to it ſelf. 2. That this argument ſtriketh no leſſe at your judgements of Neighbour Churches againſt Particular Congregations, then at that of combined Elderſhips, againſt a Particular Church; ſince your Neighbour Churches feed no more that particular Congregation, then our combined Elderſhips a particular Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We deny that our Claſſes, and Synods, or (as ye call them) combined Presbyteries, or Elderſhips, feed not particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, for they govern them, which is a certain ſort of feeding, due to Elders; and in this ſignification Kings, Princes, and Dukes are called Paſtors, or feeders of their People, becauſe they rule them, <hi>Jor.</hi> 6.3. and 12 10.</p>
               <p>But to bring more light to this captious Propoſition, and all fallacious Arguments that may be grounded hereupon, here I will more fully declare, in what ſenſe theſe Propoſitions may be true, or falſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The combined Elderſhip hath power to feed, rule, and teach the Church, or all Particular Churches. 2. The combined Elderſhip feedeth, or ruleth all Particular Churches. 3. The Elders of the combined Elderſhip have power to feed, or rule Particular Churches.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:123874:18"/>
               <p>And for this effect, note, 1. That the feeding, or teaching of the Church may be taken, either in <hi>actu ſecundo,</hi> for actuall feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or the exerciſe of the power of feeding, as when a Preacher teaches actually, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>In actu primo,</hi> for the morall power, which Miniſters have to teach in vertue of their Vocation, and Miſſion to their Charge, and Admiſſion into it. So the Power to feed (howſoever it ſignifie formally the <hi>Actum primum,</hi> as ruling <hi>Actum ſecundum</hi>) may be taken in <hi>Actu primo,</hi> for the Power, that a Miniſter hath to feed; or in <hi>Actu ſecundo,</hi> for the Act of feeding, proceeding from the power, or firſt act. 3. <hi>Item,</hi> in <hi>Actu ſignato,</hi> when a power, or an act is ſignified to belong to a thing, that exerciſeth not the act; as when a King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, but putteth it not in execution: or in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> when it is exerciſed: ſo particular Officers have the power, in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> which the King, and ſuperiour Judges, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates have in <hi>actu ſignato.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That the Miniſters, or Elders of the Elderſhip may be conſidered in quality of a collective body of Elders; or ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally every one apart; which the School-men call ordinarily <hi>collectivè, &amp; diſtributivè.</hi> If ſeverally, then either Abſolutely, without any relation to the collective body of the Elderſhip, and in quality of particular Miniſters of their own Particular Churches; or with ſome relation, or reſpect to the collective body, or combination of the Elderſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> as parts thereof.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The whole collective body of the Elderſhip may be taken, either <hi>formally,</hi> as it is a collection of ſundry Elders, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Order eſtabliſhed in the Church, repreſenting many Churches combined, and conſociated, from which they have their Commiſſions; or materially in quality of Miniſters, or Elders, of whom the Conſociation, or Combination, or Synod, or Claſſicall Aſſembly of Elders is compounded.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Both the collective body, or conſociation of Elders, which is a repreſentative body of many Churches, as alſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular reall Church, and the whole Militant Church, may be conſidered (as other things) <hi>aut ut Totum ſimpliciter, aut ut Totum, &amp; totaliter;</hi> either as a Totall, or Totally, as a Whole or wholly; ſo may we ſay of <hi>omne,</hi> it may be taken <hi>ſimpliciter pro omne, vel pro Omni, &amp; omnino, vel omni modo:</hi> this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:123874:19"/>word <hi>All,</hi> may be taken abſolutely for <hi>all,</hi> or for <hi>all,</hi> conſidered all manner of wayes, or altogether.</p>
               <p>Then a <hi>Totum</hi> is taken <hi>totaliter,</hi> or totally, or a whole thing wholly, and this word <hi>All,</hi> all wayes, when it is taken, according to all the <hi>Modifications,</hi> that it can have; As for example, <hi>Peter</hi> is a <hi>Totum,</hi> or a Whole-man, when he is lying in his Bed at <hi>Rome,</hi> he is <hi>Totus Romae,</hi> all, or whole at <hi>Rome;</hi> but not <hi>Totaliter,</hi> totally, not wholly, or all wayes; for he may ſit, and ſtand at <hi>Rome;</hi> and when he is lying, he is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe other wayes, and <hi>Modifications, viz.</hi> ſtanding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, I may ſay, that it is impoſſible, That at one time a <hi>Totum</hi> be, or exiſt in one place <hi>totum, &amp; totaliter. i. e. Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum omnes ſuos modes poſſibiles, multi enim diviſim ſunt poſſibiles ſed conjunctim incompoſſibiles;</hi> A whole thing cannot be wholly, or all wayes, or according to all its poſſible <hi>Modifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> for many of them ſeverally, or apart are poſſible, which conjunctly are incompoſſible, (if I may ſo expreſſe my ſelf) or rather impoſſible: So a man may be white, and he may be black; but he cannot be white, and black together, for theſe two qualities, being contrary, are impoſſible, or incompatible one with another.</p>
               <p>If then <hi>feeding</hi> either by way of <hi>teaching,</hi> or <hi>ruling;</hi> or the <hi>power</hi> to <hi>feed,</hi> be taken in <hi>actu primo, viz.</hi> for the <hi>facultie</hi> to feed, this Propoſition, The combined Elderſhip or a Claſſicall, or Synodall Aſſembly, and every particular Elder conſidered apart, and ſeparated from the combined Presbyteries have power to feed, teach, or rule, all particular Churches, is true. And as for the particular Elders (which may ſeem the moſt abſurd) it appeareth cleerly; for if they had it not how could ye, or they, Preach in ſundry, and divers particular Churches, as ye do, out of your own particular Churches? If it be anſwered, that ye do it onely <hi>Occaſionally,</hi> and not <hi>Ordinarily:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I reply, That before ye can do it either <hi>Occaſionally,</hi> or <hi>Ordinarily,</hi> ye muſt have a power to do it <hi>abſolutely;</hi> for <hi>actus ſecundus ſupponit primum,</hi> the ſecond act ſuppoſeth the firſt; or all actions ſuppoſe ſome active power, from whence they proceed; for a man, that is no Miniſter can neither Preach <hi>Ordinarily,</hi> nor <hi>Occaſionally.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:123874:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> It is a certain Maxime in Logick, that a <hi>Parte in modo ad Totum argument amur affirmativè, ut, eſt homo albus, Ergo, eſt homo.</hi> We argue from a <hi>modified</hi> part, or taken with ſome limitation, or modification to the <hi>whole;</hi> as if I ſay, this is a white man; <hi>Ergo,</hi> this is a man: So I ſay, this man may Preach <hi>occaſionally; Ergo,</hi> this man may Preach, or have Authoritie to Preach; <hi>For Power or Authoritie to Preach, is Totum in modo, and Power, or Authoritie to Preach occaſionally, or ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, are partes in modo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be objected, That if every particular Miniſter hath Power or Authoritie to Preach in every Church, or Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then every Miniſter is an univerſall Paſtour, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: But ſo it is not. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny the Conſequence of the firſt Propoſition, for an Apoſtle not onely hath an univerſall Vocation to teach all particular Churches, and Flocks, but alſo to teach all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and ordinary Paſtours, or Miniſters of all particular Churches, and Flocks. 2. <hi>Item,</hi> The Vocation of the Apoſtles was immediately from God. 3. They were infallible in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. 4. Endowed with extraordinarie Gifts. 5. They had no particular Miſſion, to reſtrain them to any particular Church; And theſe four laſt Conditions were moſt convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly annexed unto the Univerſalitie of their Charge, which cannot be ſaid of ordinary, and particular Miniſters.</p>
               <p>If it be replied, At leaſt they differ not from them in the Univerſalitie of their Charge, but onely in ſome Accidents, as in Infallibilitie, ſome extraordinarie Gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that are meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Extrinſecall unto the Charge, and to the Univerſalitie thereof.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, Firſt, That theſe Accidents are not meerly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall unto the Univerſalitie of the Apoſtolicall Charge, but Intrinſecally annexed unto it, by Gods Ordinance, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruitie, and Morally; ſince it could not be Univerſally exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For the better cleering of this, I obſerve, That to the Charge of a Miniſter, three things are neceſſary. 1. A generall Vocation to Preach, and that not unlike to that, which Maſters of Arts, and Doctors receive in Univerſities, with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:123874:20"/>this clauſe, <hi>Hic, &amp; ubique terrarum,</hi> to Teach here, and through all the World. 2. A ſpeciall Miſſion, either 1. by God alone; or 2. or alſo from the Repreſentative Church. 3. A particular Election, and Admiſſion, whereby the Miniſter is elected by a Reall particular Church, and ſo admitted therein to exerciſe his Charge.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe three is common to the Apoſtles, with all ordinary Miniſters: The ſecond is univerſall in the Apoſtles, for Chriſt ſent them to teach all Nations, and ſitted them with gifts convenient thereunto; But it is particular in Particular, and Ordinary Miniſters, for orders ſake, and that <hi>jure divine,</hi> as many learned, and godly Divines hold: The third, <hi>jure divine,</hi> ſhould be univerſall, in reſpect of the Apoſtles; for every Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church was bound to admit the Apoſtles, in caſe they would have preached amongſt them; and if any ſhould have refuſed them, yet in vertue of their generall Vocation, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Miſſion from God, they had power, and Authoritie to Preach among them, and in them all; But in Particular, and Ordinary Miniſters it is onely Particular, and not Univerſall; for neither doth every Particular Church chuſe, elect, or admit every Ordinary Miniſter to be its Miniſter, neither is it bound ſo to do.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe three is the remote foundation, or the remote, and principall cauſe of the Power, and Authoritie that a Miniſter hath to Preach, or to rule the Church of God: The ſecond and third are the next, and immediate foundation, or cauſe thereof, or <hi>conditio ſine qua non; viz.</hi> The univerſall Miſſion, and Admiſſion of Miniſters, is the immediate cauſe of their univerſall Power, and Authoritie; but the particular Miſſion, and Admiſſion is the immediate cauſe of the Power, and Authoritie of Particular Miniſters: And as we never finde the Philoſophers <hi>Particularia,</hi> without their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalia</hi> in <hi>Particularibus incluſa,</hi> never a <hi>Genus</hi> but in ſome <hi>Species,</hi> nor a <hi>Species</hi> but in ſome <hi>Individuum,</hi> by whoſe Differences their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Nature is limited, and determined; No more finde we over this vaſt, and generall Vocation in Ordinary Miniſters without this Particular Miſſion of ſome Repreſentative Church, and Admiſſion in, and by ſome Reall, and Particular
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:123874:20"/>Church, or at leaſt it ſhould not be; for without this conſent Election, and Admiſſion, a Miniſter is no more its Miniſter, then a Man is a Womans Husband without her conſent. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can a Man be married to a Woman in generall, or to an <hi>Individuam vagam,</hi> but to this, or that Particular Woman, with whom he contracteth: No more can a Preacher be ſent to Preach to the Church in generall, or to Particular Churches indefinitely, <hi>viz.</hi> Unto <hi>quaedam Eccleſia,</hi> but to this Church diſtinctly.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. And ſo I anſwer, that a Particular and Ordinary Miniſter is differenced from an Univerſall Miniſter, or an Apoſtle by the Particularitie of his charge, in vertue of his Particular Miſſion, which he hath of God, by a Repreſentative Church, and of his Particular Election, and Admiſſion, which depend upon that Particular Reall Church, whoſe Miniſter he is, and not in vertue of his generall Vocation, which is common unto both, <hi>Nam Principium convenientiae non eſt Principium differentiae,</hi> That wherein things do agree cannot diſtinguiſh, or make them differ.</item>
                  <item>2. Every particular, or Ordinary Miniſter may feed, teach, and rule all the Church, but not alwayes, <hi>Totam militantem Eccleſiam, ſed non totaliter,</hi> All particular Churches, but not particularly, for (as we have ſaid) he may teach in every Church, becauſe he may Preach in them, being invited there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; but he cannot Teach in them all, alwayes, in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular way, by way of a Particular, and Ordinary Miſſion, and Admiſſion, as their Particular Paſtour: For neither is he called to Teach in them all, neither can he rule them all <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctim</hi> in one time, but one onely Ordinarily, and two, or three Extraordinarily in caſe of ſome urgent neceſſitie.</item>
                  <item>3. Yea, we may ſay, That a Particular Miniſter cannot evermore, neither doth he evermore feed his own Particular Church, <hi>totam, &amp; totaliter,</hi> the whole Church, wholly, as Experience teacheth us, but ſometimes he feedeth it one way, ſometimes another, ſometimes in teaching, ſometimes in ruling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. It may be ſaid, That the conſociated, or combined Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries, and Presbyters rule all the Churches, from which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:123874:21"/>they have Commiſſion. 1. In qualitie of Particular Miniſters, as we have already declared. 2. In a Particular way in vertue of their Commiſſion from Particular Churches, in whoſe name they appear, and in vertue of their Admiſſion in a Claſſicall or Synodall Aſſembly; but not in <hi>ſenſu diviſo,</hi> every one apart, for if they diſſent in their voices from the major part of the Aſſembly, they <hi>feed</hi> no Church at all, at leaſt <hi>actually,</hi> and in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> howſoever they may be ſaid to <hi>rule</hi> them all, that be ſubject to that Aſſembly, <hi>potentia, &amp; in actu ſignato.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. The whole collective, or combined Presbyterie, or Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, being-taken collectively, or as combined, ruleth many Particular Churches, that are ſubject unto it. I ſay being taken, as combined or <hi>collectivè;</hi> for if the Presbyters of the Aſſembly be taken <hi>diſtributivè;</hi> they are not an Aſſembly, not a Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Combination of Presbyters <hi>formally,</hi> but ſeverall Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters apart, and divers unities, which are the matter of this combination, and conſociation in the Aſſembly.</item>
                  <item>6. Thoſe whole combined Presbyteries, <hi>qua tota, ſed non qua tataliter conſiderata,</hi> as whole, or totals, but not conſidered totally, feed in any Particular Churches: The firſt part is certain, for they judge of Points of Doctrine, and Diſcipline already, revealed in Holy Scripture, and give us new Eccleſiaſticall Laws of things indifferent, and ſo Teach, and Rule the Churches, which is nothing elſe but to Feed them.</item>
                  <item>7. Yet theſe combined Presbyteries being conſidered totally, <hi>viz.</hi> according to every reſpect, every part, every modification, and determination they can have, rule them not; for every one of the Combined Presbyteries have not this Power; For as we have ſaid, 2.3 4. or 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may diſſent from the major part, and in that caſe they rule not in the Aſſembly, muchleſſe rule they out of the Aſſembly, being conſidered, as Materiall parts thereof, and the reaſon is becauſe, <hi>Non quic quid convenit Toti per accidens, aggregato, confuſo, vel ordinato, id convenit ſingulu partibus;</hi> it is not needfull that whatſoever belongeth, or is attributed to the collective body, ſhould be attributed to every part thereof, ſo ten is twice five, which cannot be ſaid of five, which is a part of ten; for it is not twice, but once five.</item>
                  <item>8. Neither can theſe combined Presbyteries, or Elderſhips
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:123874:21"/>taken materially. 1. <hi>i.e.</hi> before their combination <hi>feed</hi> many Churches, as when they are combined; for in that ſenſe they are not <hi>formally</hi> a combination, or a collective body, but the <hi>matter</hi> thereof, and therefore to them cannot belong that, which belongeth unto the collective body <hi>formally,</hi> or in vertue of its forme.</item>
                  <item>9. The collective, or combined body of divers Presbyteries feeds not many reall Particular Churches <hi>in actu exercito,</hi> as if they exerciſed actually the act of feeding them in a particular way, as their Particular, and Ordinarie Miniſters do; but <hi>in actu ſignato,</hi> in ſignifying and repreſenting unto them all, in vertue of their Commiſſions, by their Judgements, and Laws, what ſhould be done by them all; which theſe Particular Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters do in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> and in a more ſpeciall way: And the reaſon of this is, becauſe, if it were not ſo we ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the charge of combined Presbyteries, with that of one Presbyter.</item>
                  <item>10. This Propoſition may yet receive this ſence; All the combined Presbyteries feed all the particular Churches, that they repreſent. 1. All the Presbyters together feed, and rule all Churches together as combined. 2. In this combination, or collection of Presbyters, or Elders, every one of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, or Elders, feedeth his own Church. 3. All the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective body of combined Elders feed every Church apart; as we ſaid before. 4. Every Presbyter, or Elder in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination ruleth all Churches, as we have declared it alſo.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1</hi> Eth. ad Nicomach. c. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> So the Philoſophers in expounding that Maxime, <hi>Bonum eſt, quod omnia appetunt,</hi> that is good which all things deſire, give us almoſt the like interpretations, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. All good things taken collectively, are thoſe, that all deſirers taken collectively do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. 2. That every one in this collection of deſirers deſireth his own good in the collection of all good; as a man, mans good; a horſe, that which is good for a horſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. That the whole collection of deſirers deſireth every good, as it ſerveth for every part, and ſo for the totall, or whole, that conſiſteth of the parts. 4. That every deſirer apart deſireth, or loveth the whole collection of good, inſomuch as in that collection of good, it findeth its own good.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:123874:22"/>
               <p>But none of theſe ſenſes approved by us, can ſerve our Bethren. More might here have been ſaid, and I hope that others, God willing, ſhall ſay more; But this may ſuffice for one Annotation, and I am aſſured, will ſufficiently diſſolve all their Arguments hitherto, founded upon this Propoſition.</p>
               <p>About the end of this 15 §. Ye ſay <hi>[That this challenge of all ſpirituall power from Chriſt, had need have a cleer pattent from Chriſt,]</hi> and that noted by a Particular Parentheſis, as very conſiderable; ſo had your Independent, and Omnipotent power within your Particular Congregations: Neither do our Synods challenge all power, but a Miniſteriall Power, ſuch as we have already expounded: Neither needs it any <hi>Pattent</hi> expreſly, and formally from Chriſt: It ſufficeth that it have one from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for that ſufficeth to binde us all unto obedience; for Chriſt as Mediator, and head of the Church is not repreſented unto us in Scripture as Author of Nature, but of Grace, <hi>For the Law was given by Moſes, but grace, and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is Mediator of a better Covenant; Neither came he to abrogate, or deſtroy, but to fulfill, and to accompliſh the Law; The Author of grace poſeth not, but preſuppoſeth the Law of Nature; And yet we can ſhew a <hi>Pattent</hi> for it, not onely from the Law of Nature, which ſhould ſuffice, but alſo from the Law of Grace, in the Old, and New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>Immediately after ye ſay, That nothing was written upon this Subject before the Books ſet forth by two Divines of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> one of <hi>England,</hi> and others of <hi>Holland.</hi> Here ye miſtake, for we can produce you ſundry others of good note, here Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>London;</hi> we are ſorry ye have not ſeen them, or diſdained to read them. If there were not many written before thoſe, it was in pittie of your afflictions, whereunto good Divines would not adde new affliction; Neither thought they your Partie ſo conſiderable; Neither were your Opinions much known or publiſhed abroad, being onely written in Engliſh, and not in Latine, except by one, or two of your Divines, for any thing I know: Neither thought they that ye were ſo averſe from their Diſcipline, as ye appear in this Aſſembly, but that ye ſuffered only for not conforming your ſelves unto Epiſcopall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:123874:22"/>Government: But whatever they have written, I know not what this can ſerve to the purpoſe, unleſſe it be to declare, That whatſoever helps ye had heretofore, yet ye were deſtitute of thoſe writings, whereby ye might have received farther light concerning Presbyteriall Government; and I pray God ye make good uſe of them.</p>
               <p>In the 16. §. at the end of the 16. <hi>Pag.</hi> Ye travell to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move an Objection, <hi>viz. That in Congregationall Government</hi> (ſuch as is amongſt you) <hi>there is no allowed ſufficient remedy for miſcarriages, though never ſo groſſe; no relief for wrongfull Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, or Perſons injured thereby; no room for Complaints: No Powerfull, or Effectuall means to reduce a Church, or Churches, that fall into Hereſie, or Schiſme, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To avoid this Objection, ye relate us an Hiſtory § 17. and what ye did upon ſuch an emergent caſe: But ye ſhew us no Law, that ever ye had amongſt you, whereby ye might bring any remedie againſt ſuch a miſcarriage before that it fell out. 2. Neither read we of any ſuch Law, or remedie in your Books, before this. 3. Your Divines, and the Members of your Churches, with whom we converſed, ſhewed no remedie amongſt you for ſuch inconveniencies. 4. They gave us no anſwer unto this Objection, ſave onely this, <hi>That God hath ordained no remedies in ſuch Caſes;</hi> Yea, that if Churches ſhould fall away from Chriſt, and with the Jews, call him an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor, and the Trinitie with <hi>Servet</hi> a three headed Cat, and deny the Incarnation of the Son of God, they ſhould be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; Yea more, That the Civill Magiſtrate ſhould puniſh no man for his Religion, be it never ſo bad, or blaſphemous; and that it muſt be left to God; And this giveth us reaſon to think, That theſe Reaſons, within theſe two yeers, have made you to refine your Opinion, and to mould ſome new Solutions, and to ſuite your Opinions more cloſe to the current of the time, then you were wont to do. If therefore we ſpeak after them, it is their fault, and not ours; it may be, that your Opinion be not common to you all, but to you five alone.</p>
               <p>The ſum of the Hiſtory is, A Miniſter was ſuddenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by his Flock, whereupon ſome Churches did take offence, and all their Churches conſented in this Principle,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:123874:23"/>
                  <hi>That Churches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.32. 1 Tim. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>as well as particular men, are bound to give no offence, neither to Jew, nor Gentile, nor the Churches of God they live among:</hi> Item, <hi>That in vertue of the ſame, or like Law of not partaking in other mens ſins, the Churches offended, may, and ought, upon the Impenitency of thoſe Churches, perſiſting in their errour, and miſcarriage, to pronounce that heavy ſentence againſt them, of withdrawing, and renouncing all Chriſtian Communion with them, untill they do repent; And further to declare, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt this, with the cauſes thereof, to all Chriſtian Churches of Chriſt, that they may do the like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Narration it appeareth. 1. That this Church offending, before this emergent Caſe, knew not ſo much, for if ſhe had, it is not credible, that ſhe would, againſt all charitie, and the common order of all Churches, have committed ſo great a ſcandall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This remedie is not ſufficient, nor ſatisfactory. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all Churches, according to your Tenets, be equall in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, Independent one of another, and <hi>par in parcm non habet Imperium,</hi> none hath power, or Authoritie over his equall; how then could any Church binde another to any ſuch account, but out of its freewill, as a partie may do to its partie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe ſince other Churches were, or pretended to be offended in ſuch a proceeding, they could not judge in it; for then they ſhould have been both judge, and partie in one cauſe, which cannot be granted to thoſe, that have no Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative Power one over another, as when a private man offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the State, and we our God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What if many Churches, yea all the Churches, ſhould offend one, ſhould that one Church gather all the reſt together, judge them all, and in caſe of not ſubmitting themſelves to her judgement, ſeparate her ſelf from them all? If ſo, we ſhould have Separations, and Schiſmes enough, which ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to all Poſteritie to come.</p>
               <p n="5">5. What if Churches were ſo remote one from another, that they could not eaſily meet together upon every occaſion? Then there ſhould be no remedy, or at leaſt no eaſie remedy.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:123874:23"/>6. What if the Offence were ſmall, ſhould ſo many Churches for every trifle gather together, and put themſelves to ſo great coſt, and trouble?</p>
               <p n="7">7. What if the Churches in their Judgements ſhould differ one from another, in ſuch a caſe ſhould they all by Schiſmes ſeparate themſelves one from another?</p>
               <p n="8">8. This ſort of Government giveth no more Power, or Authoritie to a thouſand Churches over one, then to a Tincker, yea to the Hangman over a thouſand, for he may deſire them all, out of charitie, to give an account of their Judgement, in caſe he be offended by them; Neither ſee I what more our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren grant to all the Churches of the World over one.</p>
               <p>But the Presbyteriall Government is ſubject to none of theſe inconveniencies, for the collective, or combined Elderſhip, having an authoritative Power, all men, and Churches thereof, are bound by Law, and Covenant to ſubmit themſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: Every man knoweth their ſet times of meeting, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſundry matters are diſpatched, and all things carried by plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of voices, without any Schiſme, or Separation.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This Government is a Power, wherein the Partie is judged if he will, and ſo the judgement of the Judges ſuſpended upon the judgement of the Partie judged, which is moſt ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, without any example in Eccleſiaſticall, or Civill Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories; a judgement indeed not very unlike to that which is related of a merry man, who ſaid he had the beſt, and moſt obedient wife of the whole World, becauſe (ſaith he) ſhe will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing but what I will, and as all men wondred at it, (knowing her to be the moſt diſobedient) yea (ſaith he) but I muſt firſt will what ſhe willeth, elſe ſhe willeth nothing, that I will.</p>
               <p n="10">10. This ſort of Government is unjuſt, and unreaſonable, for not onely the Partie judgeth its Partie, but alſo it inflicteth the ſame puniſhment, <hi>viz.</hi> Separation, upon all offending Churches, what ever be the offence, great, or ſmall in caſe of Non-ſatisfaction, whereas all puniſhments ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate unto the ſeverall offences.</p>
               <p n="11">11. And ſo ye ſeem to approve the opinion of the Stoicks, who held all ſins to be equall, ſince ye inflict the ſame puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon them all.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:123874:24"/>12. Not onely this Diſcipline cannot eaſily be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in great Kingdoms, as <hi>England,</hi> wherein all the Churches offended, cannot ſo eaſily meet together, but alſo 13. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the perſon offended after he hath repreſented his grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces unto one Church, and that Church having received ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, it may go to another, and that Church likewiſe having received ſatisfaction, it may go to another, and ſo continually in <hi>infinitum</hi> to the Worlds end, evermore taking thoſe Churches for the Partie that judge it, which is moſt abſurde and fooliſh.</p>
               <p n="14">14. What if the Partie offended be poor, and have not the means to poſt up and down from Neighbour-Church to Neighbour-Church, to pray them to make the offending Church to give an account of her Judgement, muchleſſe to attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their uncertain conveniencie: Here will be found true, <hi>Pauper ubique jacet,</hi> whereas in Presbyteriall Government the Partie offended may eaſily be redreſſed, and get ſatisfaction, as not having need ſo to poſt up and down, to be at ſo great charges, or to attend their conveniencie, for by a ſimple Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal he may binde the Church offending, to appear at the day appointed.</p>
               <p n="15">15. What if there ſhould fall out an hundred ſuch Offences in a ſmall time? Muſt ſo many Churches evermore gather together for every one of them apart?</p>
               <p n="16">16. What if Churches be poor, and cannot be at ſo great expence? Then in that caſe, it ſhould ſeem, there is no order to meet with Offences.</p>
               <p>And as for thoſe precepts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. The firſt of them is not a Rule of Government, or ruling of the Church, but a generall command, common to all Chriſtians, whereby the Apoſtle forewarnes the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in things indifferent, not to give any occaſion of Offence unto the Church of God, or to any other; but therein to comply with all men, as he doeth himſelf: From whence ye cannot draw a Rule, or Law of <hi>ruling</hi> the Church, or how the Church ſhould take order with ſuch Offenders; ſo that it ſheweth, indeed, every mans dutie towards the Church, in things indifferent; but not the Churches dutie towards every one of them, in judging or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:123874:24"/>ruling. Ye might as well have proved it from this Principle, <hi>Fly from all evil;</hi> or from that, <hi>We muſt love God above all things, and our Neighbour as our ſelves:</hi> neither ſee I any greater connexion that it hath with the one, then with the other. And truely I cannot ſufficiently admire, how out of that Principle, <hi>Give no offence,</hi> ne <hi>to any man,</hi> ye can inferre this concluſion, <hi>Ergo,</hi> a Church offended may make a Church offending to give an account of her judgement before all the world; and in caſe of impenitency, pronounce a Sentence of withdrawing, and renouncing all Chriſtian Communion with her; and further to declare it to all other Churches.</p>
               <p>No more can it be inferred of the other, <hi>viz. Be not parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in other mens ſins;</hi> for the Apoſtle there giveth <hi>rules</hi> about the Vocation of Miniſters, forbiddeth <hi>Timothy</hi> to receive any man raſhly into the Miniſtery, leaſt in ſo doing he be the cauſe of an unlawfull Vocation, becauſe, ſaith he, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. their ſin, and incapacity will ſoon appear to all men. But how is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible out of this to ſpin out the former Coucluſion?</p>
               <p>§ 18. <hi>Pag.</hi> 17, ye prove your former Concluſion thus: 1. For that ye ſaw <hi>no further authority in Scripture in proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings purcly Eccleſiaſticall, of one or many ſiſter Churches towards another whole Church, or Churches offending.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe no other Authority can rationally be put in execution without the Magiſtrates power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Ye ſaw no more in Scripture; yea, but ſaw ye your own Concluſion in Scripture? 2. Truely we ſee no Word of God for it; and if we take it not upon your word, we ſhall never take it. 3. If ye ſee no Scripture for it, yet others may ſee. 4. Ye may, if ye will, ſee it in the ordinary Practice of the Church of the Jews in the old Teſtament, which is not abrogated in the New, ſince it is not Ceremoniall, but ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Law of Nature: Ye may ſee it in the Hiſtory of the New Teſtament, in the judgement given out at the Synod of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> concerning the buſineſſe of <hi>Antiochia;</hi> which I hope, ye ſhall ſee cleerly demonſtrated to you by a better hand, before it be long.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It may be proved by the Law of Nature, which is a <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognitum</hi> to Scripture, and ſuppoſed by Scripture; for <hi>Grace</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:123874:25"/>is not <hi>deſtructory</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> but a <hi>Superſtructory</hi> above <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> So that when Scripture containeth nothing contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Dictats of <hi>Nature,</hi> we are bound to believe them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we will misbelieve God, who is no leſſe the Author of <hi>Nature,</hi> and of the Dictats thereof, then of <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe no <hi>other Authority can rationally be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without the Civill Magiſtrates power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Our Brethren here, as every where elſe, ſtand very ſtiffly to Negations; They never prove any poſitive Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and it is known in the Schools, how eaſie a thing it is to deny all things, and to prove nothing: If they had that to prove, wherein they agree with us, I ſuppoſe they ſhould have more to do, then we to prove that, wherein they diſagree from us.</p>
               <p>But to take away all miſtakes, and captious Evaſions, we ſuppoſe that our Churches arrogate to themſelves no Imperiall, or Magiſteriall, but onely a Miniſteriall Power, or Authority. 2. That it is meerly Spirituall, conſiſting 1. in the Creation, Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion, and Depoſition of Church-Officers. 2. in determining matters of Doctrine. 3. in making of Eccleſiaſticall Laws, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things indifferent. 4. in Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures, as in Suſpenſion, Excommunication, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They prove, That no more can rationally be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> then to call an offending Church to an account; and in caſe of her impenitency, to declare it to all other Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We deny the Aſſumption. They prove it, for that Chriſt gave no power to Churches to excommunicate their neighbour Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This is again another miſtake in our Brethren, for they ſuppoſe, that we excommunicate whole Churches, which we never do. 2. Neither believe I, that they can bring us any examples of it: The reaſon why we do not ſo, is, Becauſe whole Churches ordinarily amongſt us, contemn not the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Eccleſiaſticall Power, <hi>viz.</hi> of Synods, being bound by their Oath, and Covenant, to obſerve, and maintain the Order of the Church. 3. And therefore we have no Eccleſiaſticall Laws concerning ſuch caſes, for <hi>Lex eſt ordinatio rationis,</hi> and Laws are not made of things that never fall out, or of things
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:123874:25"/>that fall out extraordinarily, but of things that are ordinary 4 Much leſſe think I, that ever any ſuch caſe did fall out in any one of the Reformed Churches. <hi>Item,</hi> it is another miſtake, to ſuppoſe, that there is no Excommunication, but in giving the offender over to Satan: That is indeed the higheſt degree of Excommunication, but not all the degrees of it; for there is another leſſe, and inferiour, <hi>viz.</hi> in ſeparating him from Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Communion: And ſo it is yet another miſtake in you to think, that in declaring your non-Communion with other Churches, ye do not excommunicate them; for what is Excommunication, but a privation of communion; the very word it ſelf teacheth us all this.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If any ſuch Caſe ſhould extraordinarily fall out, how can it be denyed, but that the particular Church offending might be excommunicated by the reſt of the Churches offended, if the offence ſhould deſerve it. 1. For we finde nothing in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the contrary. 2. For there is the ſame reaſon for the Excommunication of whole Churches, as of particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>viz.</hi> the taking away of ſcandall, and the converſion of the ſinner, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. and that ſuch a contagion infect not others, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 6, 7. And if a particular man may be excommunicated for denying, and blaſpheming of Chriſt, wherefore ſhall not a particular Church be excommunicated for the like ſin? Neither can their number and conſociation excuſe them, but rather aggravateth the ſin; for the more offenders there be, the greater is the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and the greater ſhould the puniſhment be.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If a Church compounded of ten perſons may excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate four of their own number, wherefore alſo may not ten thouſand Churches excommunicate this inconſiderable Church, compounded of ten perſons, for the ſame reaſons that it excommunicateth four perſons? hath God given more power to ten perſons over four, then to all the perſons, and Churches in the Kingdom, yea in all the Chriſtian world, over theſe miſerable, and wretched perſons, who (it may be) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Trinity, the Incarnation of the Son of God, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all ſort of impieties?</p>
               <p n="4">4. If God in Heaven, and in his Scripture declare a Church
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:123874:26"/>excommunicated, wherefore ſhall not his Churches upon Earth alſo declare it excommunicated, when they learn it in his Word? Are not the Churches of God as well bound to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his Sentence here upon Earth, as he to ratifie theirs in Heaven?</p>
               <p n="5">5. We have ſome examples of it in the Old Teſtament; for the people of God (ſay ſome of our Divines) excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated <hi>Amalck;</hi> for proof whereof, they bring the <hi>Targum, Cant.</hi> 2. <hi>Contriverunt Amalek per diram imprecationem, They bruiſed Amalek by the fearfull curſing of the Lord.</hi> So did they the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> becauſe of the building of their Temple upon the Mount <hi>Garizim.</hi> They brought (as <hi>Druſius,</hi> and after him <hi>Weemſe,</hi> relate it) 300 Prieſts, 300 Trumpets, 300 Books of the Law, and 300 Boyes; They blew with Trumpets, and the Levites ſinging, accurſed the <hi>Cutthaans</hi> in the Name of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tragammaton,</hi> or <hi>Jehova,</hi> and with curſes both the ſuperiour, and inferiour houſe of Judgement; and they ſaid, <hi>Curſed is be, who cateth the bread of the Cutthaean.</hi> Theſe Curſes they wrote upon Tables, and ſealed them, and ſent them thorow all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who multiplied alſo this great <hi>Anathema</hi> upon them; from whence proceeded a great hatred betwixt them, as we reade in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>If in vertue of a ſmall offence one Church may pronounce that dreadfull Sentence of non-Communion, againſt many Churches, wherefore may not many Churches pronounce Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of great Excommunication againſt one ſmall Church, for a great ſin? ſince <hi>creſcentibus delictis creſcunt poenae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides all this, I deny the conſequence; for howbeit God had not ordained Excommunication, <hi>viz.</hi> the greater, which here ye underſtand, yet might there be ſome other remedy found by the light of Nature.</p>
               <p>But ye adde, <hi>p.</hi> 18. That your Sentence of non-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication will be as effectuall as the greater Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>This cannot be, 1. Becauſe, if the offender have any grace, the greater will terrifie him more. 2. Becauſe in your way the Sentence may ſeem unjuſt, in puniſhing all offences, and Offenders, greater and ſmaller with the like Spirituall penalties.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:123874:26"/>3. Your way cannot ſo well awe Churches, and keep them in their duties; for ſince ye attribute no authoritative power, or authority to all the Churches of Chriſt over any particular Church, but judge them all to be equall amongſt themſelves, and one to all; as if a part were equall to its totall, and <hi>pars eſſet aequalis Toti, &amp; Totum non eſſet majus quilibet ſuâ parte,</hi> as if the part were equall to its whole, and the whole were no greater then its part, <hi>viz.</hi> a whole mans body then his toe; a particular Church may think her ſelf no ways bound to obey any other Church, or Churches: and much leſſe will ten Churches think themſelves bound to obey one; for Obediecce is a vertue in Inferiours towards their Superiours: But if all Churches be equall, there can neither be Superiours, nor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, and conſequently no obedience, or diſobedience.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If a particular Church, in your way, deſire to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by fourty Churches, pretending her ſelf to be offended by their proceedings, they may think her bold, in calling them to an account, and that the ſpirits of Prophets ſhould be ſubject to Prophets, one rather to twenty, or two thouſand, then twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or two thouſand to one.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In our way, a Church offending may eſteem her offence greater, and fear it more, ſince ſhe may judge her ſelf to offend two Authorities, 1. that of God, and 2. that which he hath given unto the Church: but in yours ſhe cannot think her of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſo great, ſince ſhe conceives her ſelf to offend one au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or authoritative Power onely, <hi>viz.</hi> that of God; for ye acknowledge no authoritative power in the Church, or Churches, and ſo your way breedeth a plain contempt of all Church Authority.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In denying an authoritative power, the offender may think you too buſie bodies in intermedling your ſelves with other folks matters, which concerns you not ſo much; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, if ye granted an authoritative power unto her, it ſhould be her own proper buſineſſe, in vertue of her authoritative power received from God.</p>
               <p>So alſo our way is more efficacious in the Churches of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; 1. in breeding a greater deteſtation of ſin: 2. in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to ſhun and avoyd more the company of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:123874:27"/>offender. 3. in making them to conceive the Sentence to be more juſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> if this your way be as efficacious, ye need no other power, in your particular Congregations, over particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; a ſimple admonition, without any authoritative power, may ſuffice you.</p>
               <p>Ye yet ſay, That your way is <hi>more brotherly</hi> in proceeding without an <hi>Authoritative power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> God in the Old Teſtament ordained an Authoritative power in the Church, and yet they were all Brethren; and he knew well enough what power was convenient for Brethren.</p>
               <p n="2">2. So likewiſe in particular Congregations we are all Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, neither yet will ye baniſh out of them all Authority.</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">2 Kin 6.21. 1 Cor 14, 15 2 Cor. 6 13. and 12.14. Gal 4 19. 1 Theſ 2.11 1 Tim. 1.2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.4. Phil 2.10. 1 Ioh. 2.1.28 and 3.7 and 4.4.</note> The Miniſters, and the Elders are not onely our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but alſo our Fathers; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they muſt as well uſe pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall authority over us, as brotherly charity towards us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. So alſo combined Presbyteries, or (as it were) Fathers of ſimple Presbyteries, becauſe of their greater power to judge.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The like of this Government hath never been heard of in the world, neither in State, nor Common-wealth before; and therefore ſeemeth it to us to be repugnant unto the Law of Nature; for what elſe is the Law of Nature, but the common conſent of all men? How abſurd therefore is that Government, ſo deſtitute of all authority? have the ſheep as great authoirty, as the Sheepherd? if ſo, it is as good to be a ſheep as a Sheepherd.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If an Authoritative power cannot hold in the Church, or among Churches, becauſe that we are all Brethren, and Siſters, no more can it hold in the State betwixt King, and Subject; the father, and the ſon; the maſter, and the ſervant; for we are all Brethren in Chriſt: ſo this Foundation, or Ground-work, will deſtroy all ſort of Politicall, and Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Authority. Our Brethren would do well alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether their Grounds, or thoſe of our Government, will better conſiſt with the Authority of the civill Magiſtrate; for, according to this reaſon, a King in a State ſhould have no power at all over his Brother.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In the State there be divers Judicatories, Superiour, and Inferiour, wherein the Superiour hath an authoritative power
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:123874:27"/>over the inferiour. <hi>Ergo,</hi> in the Church, ſince there is the ſame reaſon for both, <hi>viz.</hi> reparation of the offence taken at inferiour Judicatories.</p>
               <p>But becauſe ye will ſeem to be much addicted to the civill Magiſtrate, as if your Eccleſiaſticall Government were alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſubordinate unto his power, and blame us, as not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him his due, which ye note by a particular Parentheſis, as if ye would have us to take particular notice of it; Therefore, before we end this Section, we ſhall be very willing to do it. In ſaying that the Presbyteriall Excommunication is no more effectuall then your Sentence of non-Communion, without the Magiſtrates Power, ye adde this Parentheſis <hi>[To which we give as much, and [as we think] more then the Principles of the Presbyteriall Government will ſuffer them to yeeld.]</hi> By whoſe counſell, or for what end this Parentheſis is inſerted, and ſuch a compariſon made. I know not; If ye have no Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ayms, I am aſſured ye comply very much with Policy. If ye grant him ſo much, ye would do well to declare how much, and wherein, and not to feed him with generalities, and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicall Idees, as abſtract here from all matter, as ye profeſſed formerly your Church-Government was abſtracted from all other Governments. It is a Maxime in Philoſophy, and in Rhetorick both, That <hi>Sermones generales non movent;</hi> and praiſed be God that the King and Parliament are wiſe, and will not feed upon ſo abſtract forms. As for us, ſince ye keep your ſelves upon ſuch generalities, it is impoſſible to us to anſwer any thing in particular, unleſſe we gueſſe at your meaning: In generall therefore we ſay, 1. That amongſt men well bred, all compariſons are odious. 2. That either ye give unto the civill Magiſtrate onely his due, or ſomething more: if onely his due, ye lay a very heavie aſperſion upon all Presbyterians, as if they were not good Subjects, in denying him a part of his due: If more, who gave you the power to do ſo? 3. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye grant him more in Civill, or in Spirituall matters: In Civill matters ye cannot; for ye can grant him no more, then he hath by the Laws of the Land, whereunto we are all equally ſubject; and therefore muſt grant him as much one, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: If in Spirituall matters, we grant him his externall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:123874:28"/>power, as we declared in the beginning. And for intrinſecall Spirituall power, 1. It is not in your power to grant him any at all; neither can ye give him more Spirituall obedience then Scripture permitteth you, or give him a part of the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power that ye have received of God; for that were, to lay upon another the burden, that God hath laid upon you, and ſo ſerve God by a Proctor. 2. It is onely in God, who is King in this Spirituall Kingdom, Maſter in this Houſe, and a Father in this Family, who can give power therein to any man: we dare not be ſo bold: If ye pretend to do it; I ſay with the Comick Poet, <hi>de te largitor puer,</hi> be liberall upon your own purſe. 4 If ye will do ſo, look how Authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is your power, who take Authority over Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and diſpoſe of it, as if it were your own: ſo do not the Presbyterians. 5. The Civill Magiſtrate acknowledgeth himſelf to be a Politicall, and no Eccleſiaſticall perſon, ſince he is neither Paſtor, nor Doctor, nor Ruling Elder in Chriſts Church; and therefore arrogateth no Spirituall Authority to himſelf 6. We deſire to know of you, Brethren, what ye underſtand here by the Magiſtrate, Whether the Supreme, or Subaltern? If the Supreme, whether the King, or Parliament? and principally at this time: If the Subaltern, we ask of you, Whether every Juſtice of Peace ſhall, or can judge of all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall matters? And if he cannot, whether he can be a competent Judge? 7. What if the Civill Magiſtrate be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt? what if ſome of the Kings Councell be Papiſts, or Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodox, as ſome in the beginning of this Parliament were? will ye grant that they judge in matters of Religion? So the Turk, the Antichriſt, and Pagans, ſhall judge in matters of Religion, amongſt their Proteſtant Subjects: If ſo, our Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Polonia,</hi> and otherwhere, are in a very fair way; Its pity but ſuch a Maxime ſhould have been publiſhed in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, and at Saint <hi>Bartholomews</hi> day in <hi>France,</hi> at that Butchery, or Maſſacre of Proteſtants. 8. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. findes fault with the Chriſtians, that did plead before Infidels in civill matters: what then would he not have ſaid, if godly men would have pleaded before them, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted matters of Religion unto their judgement? 9. This
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:123874:28"/>power that ye grant to the Magiſtrate, is either Internall, or Externall, in regard of the Church: If Externall we grant it, as well as ye: If Internall; then he muſt be an Eccleſiaſticall Perſon. And then 10. It ſhould follow, That a Soveraign Prince ſhould as well be Soveraign in the Church, as in the State; and ſo Internall head of both; which is derogatory to Chriſts Royaltie, as our Doctors have ſundry times cleerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated it againſt the Jeſuites, and other Papiſts. 11. Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that are commanded to be ſilent in the Church, ſhould rule it, and command men in it, ſince they may be Soveraign Princes in it, and over it and ſo <hi>Legliſe tomberoit on quenvillo:</hi> And if it be replyed, wherefore may they not as well rule the Church, as the State, as ſome Independenters, and ſome Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, here in <hi>London,</hi> have maintained, in preſence of their Preacher, uncontradicted by him, or any of that Profeſſion there. I anſwer, 1. Becauſe the Church or Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, is not a Kingdom of this Word. 2. Becauſe God forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the one in Scripture, but not the other. 12. Chriſts Kingdom, <hi>viz.</hi> His Church which is not of this World, ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Kings and Kingdoms of this World. 13. Yea, the Apoſtles ſhould have been ſubject unto worldly Kings in Church Government, and ſo they ſhould not have been the firſt Officers in the Church; but the King ſhould have been above them, which is no leſſe, then cleerly to contradict. Saint <hi>Paul, Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> 4. where he calleth them the firſt. 14 So wo Idly Princes could not be judged by any Church-Officers, for if they were ſupreme Judges, inferiour Officers could not judge them. 15. A King uſurping, or invading a Kingdom, ſhould uſurpe Soveraigntie in the Church. And 16. if he were a Tyrant, and obtained it <hi>jure belli,</hi> by the Sword, he ſhould make himſelf Head of the Church by the Sword, which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a very ſtrange Conqueſt of Eccleſiaſticall Authoritie. 17. If a Prince ſhould buy a Principalitie, and the Soveraigntie thereof, he ſhould conſequently buy the charge to be ſupreme Ruler, or to be above the Church, as ye call it; ſo it ſhould be a good Conqueſt, by good Simony. 18. So if a wicked Prince, ſhould invade a good Prince, againſt Gods Will, then he ſhould be Head of Chriſts Church, or ſupreme Judge over it, againſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:123874:29"/>Chriſts Will, and that by an ordinary way, yea, <hi>jure divino,</hi> by Chriſts Ordinance; if <hi>jure divino</hi> they be above the Church, as ye ſay. 19. If a Prince were perpetually mad, his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall madneſſe ſhould no more hinder him from being ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Judge in the Church, then Prince in the State. 20. If a Prince were ſupreme Judge alone, then ſhould he alone judge, yea, without his Counſell, as ſome Princes do arrogate unto themſelves; and there ſhould be the ſame Diſputes about the Princes ſupreme Authoritie in the Church, that are about it in the State. 21. God will have no man to be a Judge in his Church, but after examination, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. muchleſſe a ſupreme Judge in it: But Kings are not examined, whether they have the capacitie to rule, or not; and if the Prince be a little childe, how can he have the capacitie, or abide an examination. 22. If a King have any other, or more intrinſecall Authoritie over the Church, then all Proteſtant Churches in <hi>France, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> grant him, or then we have declared, we pray you ſhew us, what it is, and wherein it conſiſteth: Whether he hath it in qualitie of a King, of a Chriſtian, or of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King? If he hath it, in qualitie of a King, or as a King, then all Kings have it, yea, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro,</hi> and <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate; <hi>Nam quod alicui comunit quà tali communit omni.</hi> And then I pray you, whether ye will admit ſuch a Prince to judge of the Controverſies of your Religion? If in qualitie of a Chriſtian, then all Chriſtians have it, for the ſame reaſon, yea every Cobbler as well as any King, or Prince, ſince they be all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. 3. If as a Chriſtian Prince, then all Princes ſhould have it: But ſo it is not; For what if we had a Chriſtian Prince, who were a Lutheran, an Anabaptiſt, a Sociman, or a Papiſt? I cannot beleeve that ye would permit ſuch Chriſtian Princes to judge, muchleſſe to be ſupreme Judges in your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: If ye ſay that ye underſtand an Orthodox Prince? What if he had one, or two errours, would ye yet permit him to judge of Eccleſiaſticall matters? Then who ſhould judge, whether he were Orthodox, or not? Whether ye, or we? What if there were a hundred divers Sects in any Kingdom, Then he could onely judge of that Sect, which he ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and of no other: Or if he ſhould judge of all, he ſhould
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:123874:29"/>condemn them all, but his own. If by the ſupreme Magiſtrate, ye underſtand a Parliament, then to judge every one of your differences, when ever any man challengeth the Church of an unjuſt judgement, or appealeth from it, we muſt gather a Parliament: Which if the King and Parliament finde expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, I have nothing to ſay againſt it; yet every man may judge, whether the diſpatch of buſineſſe can be ſo quick and cheap, as in the Presbyterian way? What if Parliament men be of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Religions, ſhall they of one Religion judge of the other Religion.</p>
               <p>I might bring more Arguments, and proſecute them all more fully; but this may ſuffice for Annotations: Onely this I adde. 1. That it is not equitable that ye five be beleeved upon your ſimple word, in ſo great an Aſperſion, as ye lay upon ſo many Churches, yea all the beſt Reformed Churches, without any proof: If heretofore they gave you the right hand of fellowſhip, I doubt if after ſo criminall an accuſation, they will continue it to you any longer. And here I cannot ſufficiently admire you, in pretending your Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be ſo compleat, and perfect, and yet ſtand inſomuch need of the Civill Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I pray the Reader to conſider diligently. § 20. <hi>Pag.</hi> 20, 21. How by that Speech it appeareth. 1. That that Church pretended to have offended, did arrogate in diſpoſing of her Miniſter, a power altogether independent from all other, both of the Civill Magiſtrate, and of all other Churches; Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that expreſſion ſhould have been impertinent. <hi>viz. That it was the moſt to be abhorred Maxime, that any Religion hath ever made profeſſion of; and therefore of all other, the moſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory, and diſhonourable to that of Chriſtianitie, that a ſingle, and particular ſocietie of men, profeſſing the name of Chriſt, and pretending to be endowed with a power from Chriſt, to judge them, that are of the ſame body, and ſocietie within themſelves, ſhould further arrogate unto themſelves an exemption from giving an account or being cenſurable by any other, either Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate above them, or Neighbour Churches about them.</hi> For if ſhe pretended no ſuch power and exemption, to what purpoſe ſuch an expreſſion?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:123874:30"/>2. That in this Eccleſiaſticall Judgement, that is intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call to the Church, they acknowledge the Civill Magiſtrate to be above them, but all the Churches of the Chriſtian World nothing but about them, whereof much may be ſaid. Here ye ſymbolize with <hi>Eraſtus</hi> in many things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Ye may collect, that ſuch a moſt abhorred Maxime was not the Maxime of that Church alone, but of ſome others alſo, for it is not credible, that ſhe would have ſtood out alone in a Maxime ſo repugnant to the Tenets of all other Churches, and after wards ſubmitted her ſelf unto their judgement.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Ye may ſee by the event and ſucceſſe of this buſineſſe, a correction of that Maxime, wherewith they were tinctured before.</p>
               <p n="5">5. How God in his moſt wiſe Providence has forced thoſe good men, out of meer neceſſitie, to come neerer unto Presbyteriall Government, then formerly.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But we know not, whether they of <hi>New-England,</hi> will ſtand faſt to them in this deciſion.</p>
               <p>If we knew all the Circumſtances of that proceeding, we might (it may be) ſay much more, then upon ſuch a ſuperficiall, and unwilling Relation as ye make, we can ſay here.</p>
               <p>Again, I pray you note, That they acknowledge their Churches to be bound to give an account, and to be cenſurable by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, and Neighbour Churches, in their judgements. From whence I infer: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Their power is not full perfect, and compleat, within themſelves, but receives ſome correction, and perfection from that of the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate above them, or Neighbour Churches about them; But what is this, but an authoritative power to correct them, and to inflict on them ſpirituall puniſhments. <hi>viz.</hi> Cenſures, in commanding them to ſatisfie the Partie offended, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe their fault: Neither do the Presbyterians pretend to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict any corporall puniſhment, or pecuniary mulcts, ſince the aym of their Government is ſpirituall, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſave the ſoul, not to kill the body, or empty the purſe by catching mens money.</p>
               <p>§. 22. <hi>Pag</hi> 22. Ye give an account of your proceedings ſince your return to your Countrey: And here again, ye terme
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:123874:30"/>the Reformation of the Proteſtant Churches by the name of Calvinian, as if this name in this matter pleaſed you above all others; yet will we not retaliate it unto you, in calling your Churches Goodwinians, Nyans, Bridgians, Burrougheſians, Sympſonians, or Good-Ny Bridg-Burrough-Sympſonians, for we take no pleaſure in ſuch fictions.</p>
               <p>Afterwards ye give your five judgements, about that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, <hi>viz. That our Churches ſtand in need of a further Reformation.</hi> 1. But ſtand not yours in need of ſome further Reformation alſo? 2. Neither is it in queſtion, whether our Churches ſtand in need of any further Reformation? But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſtand in need of that, which ye call <hi>Reformation?</hi> And if it be not rather a <hi>Deformation,</hi> then a <hi>Reformation</hi> of the Church of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>The Reaſons of this your judgement, are grounded upon meer Poſſibilities, and generalities as we ſhall ſee God willing hereafter.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, <hi>Becauſe it may be thought, that they coming new out of Popery, and the founders of that Reformation not having Apoſtolique infallibitie might not be fully perfect the firſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It may be, but <hi>a poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non valet conſequentia:</hi> 2. It followeth not, it may be: <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is. Neither will ye permit us to argue in this manner, Maſter <hi>Goodwin,</hi> Maſter <hi>Nays, &amp;c.</hi> opinion may be falſe: <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is falſe. 3. Muchleſſe may it be thought, or imagined: <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is ſo. For we think all your Tenets, wherein ye diſſent from us, are falſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true; Neither will ye grant it for all our thoughts: No more will we grant you what ye pretend for all your thoughts, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ye bring us ſome better reaſon; for many mens thoughts be erroneous, as yours in this particular. 4. Your Argument is <hi>a Genere ad Specicm affirmativè,</hi> ye argue affirmatively from a generalitie to a particular. <hi>viz.</hi> It might not be fully perfect or imperfect: <hi>Ergo,</hi> In this or that point it was not perfect, or imperfect. 5. Neither is it needfull to a perfect Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in Doctrine, or Diſcipline, that we have an Apoſtolicall perfection, that is Perſonall, or tyed unto our Perſon; but Scripturall, <hi>viz.</hi> Revealed in Scripture, which we have, not of one, but of many Prophets, Evangeliſts, and Apoſtles.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:123874:31"/>6. This expreſſion of yours, <hi>viz. Might not be fully perfect the firſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> is ambiguous, and may be taken either <hi>Negative</hi> in putting the negation <hi>(not)</hi> before the principall Verbe, <hi>viz. might;</hi> or <hi>Infinite,</hi> in putting of it, after the Verbe, <hi>might,</hi> before the infinitie Verbe, <hi>be:</hi> In the firſt way, the ſenſe of it is this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They that come</hi> new from Popery, without Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call infallibility, cannot be perfect the firſt day, or it was not poſſible they ſhould be perfect the firſt day, and ſo it is evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe; for it ſhould imply a contradiction that any man, or Church could have a perfect Doctrine, or Diſcipline without an Apoſtolicall infallibilitie, or a long time.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond way, the ſenſe is this,</p>
               <p>They that come new from Popery, without Apoſtolicall infallibilitie may not be perfect, or it is poſſible they be not perfect, the firſt day; and ſo it is true: But as it is poſſible they be not perfect; ſo is it poſſible by Gods mercy they be perfect: And ſo the Argument will proceed <hi>a poſſe ad eſſe,</hi> whereof Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians ſay, <hi>Non valet conſequentia.</hi> So your Argument is naught: Of theſe two Propoſitions the firſt is Negative, and the laſt Infinite: They differ as,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Non poſſibile eſt eſſe</l>
                  <l>Poſſibile eſt non eſſe.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The one hath the Mood, or Modification Negative, the other the Subject, or <hi>Dictum</hi> Negative; the one is true, and the other falſe, as ye may ſee in theſe Examples.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>It was not poſſible to <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall to fall: Falſe.</item>
                  <item>It was poſſible to <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall not to fall: True. So.</item>
                  <item>It is not poſſible that <hi>Peter</hi> ſleep: Falſe.</item>
                  <item>It is poſſible that <hi>Peter</hi> ſleep not: True.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Neither doth time contribute ſo much, neither hath it any influence upon true Religion, which is a gift of God; Faith is not acquired by our labour, but infuſed into our underſtanding by Gods Mercy. And yet we have had more time, and a greater number of able men then ye, to perfect our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And as it was poſſible, that the Reformation of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:123874:31"/>our Church was not perfect the firſt day. So may it be poſſible that yours be not perfect, neither the firſt, nor the laſt day.</p>
               <p>But ye grant us, § 5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. That the firſt Reformers in Proteſtant Churches had a moſt happy hand in the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Doctrine, and that in the beginning, and without any Apoſtolicall infallibilitie; wherefore I pray then, might they not alſo have it as well in Diſcipline, or Government? I remit the Reader to that Section and my Annotation thereupon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Your ſecond Reaſon is grounded not onely upon poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, but alſo upon hope, for <hi>it may be hopefully conceived</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>that God in his infinite mercy and purpoſe reſerved, and provided ſome better thing for this Nation, when it ſhould come to be reformed, that the other Churches might not be made</hi> perfect without it, <hi>as the Apoſtle ſpeaks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This is but <hi>a poſſibile eſt eſſe,</hi> it may be, <hi>quod nihil ponit in eſſe,</hi> that maketh nothing to be: The queſtion is not what may be; but what is in effect. 2. And as it may be, ſo may it not be. 3. It is not ſo much as a may be of any thing, that is to be, but a may be, or a poſſible hope of a thing, that may be: O how far is this Reaſon from proving the thing to be. 4 And as for that Text of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.48. Ye abuſe mightily the place of Scripture, or are abuſed; for it is not to be underſtood of you, or of your, or our Reformation; but of the coming of Chriſt, and the vocation of the Gentiles; for howſoever the Fathers in the old Teſtament received the Promiſes; yet received they not the accompliſhment, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of them, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt manifeſted in the fleſh, who is that better thing, reſerved unto us, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth there, otherwiſe we ſhould have periſhed.</p>
               <p>§ 23, 24 25, 26, 27. Containeth an Enumeration of our Brethrens grievances, whereof they have mentioned many heretofore. 1. The <hi>miſtaking, and miſapprehenſion</hi> of their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, <hi>wherein they might ſeem to differ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have anſwered already. 1. It is not a miſtake, nor miſapprehenſion to take and apprehend an opinion as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the Partie, as we have done. 2. We anſwer, That if we miſtake, or miſapprehend any opinion, it is not that of all Independents. 3. It is a great miſtake in you to imagine;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:123874:32"/>that ye be all of one opinion; For ye five, who are the Authors of this Book cannot agree among your ſelves, how muchleſſe with others. 4. And we are aſſured, that ye cannot but miſtake one another. 5. Here alſo muſt be noted your Parentheſis <hi>[wherein we might ſeem to differ.]</hi> Then your differences from us were not reall, but apparent: If ſo, wherefore then will ye not really agree, and joyn your ſelves in Union and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with us? And truely ſo it is, either they are not reall, or they are really ridiculous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 23. Your ſecond grievance is, that ye are grievouſly calumniated with reproaches of Schiſme: Schiſme is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacious Separation from the true Church after ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction: And as Hereſie, as Hereſie, is repugnant to Faith ſo is Schiſme to Charitie; the one quitteth the unitie of the Faith, the other the union in Charitie: And as Hereſie is evermore accompanied with pertinacy after ſufficient conviction: So is Schiſme alſo.</p>
               <p>If therefore the Synod, or any other Aſſembly, or any of your Brethren ſhould convict you ſufficiently, and afterwards, ye ſhould ſeparate your ſelves, or deſire a <hi>ſeparation</hi> from us, I think that no man could deny you to be Schiſmaticks; neither beleeve I, in ſuch a caſe, that ye would, or could honeſtly deny i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your ſelves; But ſo long as the Synod, or ſome others does it not, I dare ſay nothing: As for my ſelf, I beleeve truly, that ye be very Learned, Pious, and honeſt Men; and howſoever ye may fail by infirmitie, yet beleeve I not, that ye erre out of malice; and conſequently, that ye are no Schiſmaticks hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. And I hope, and am conſident, that God will not permit, that ſo good, and godly men fall away from his Church. And this I ſay by morall probabilitie, becauſe of the good opinion I have conceived of you, by good mens relations, and ſome obſervation of your carriages, in the ſmall converſation I have had with ſome of you. If therefore any men out of too much zeal, or others out of malice, have uttered any ſuch aſperſion, it is in your power, by entertaining of a Fraternall union with us to give them the ly, as I hope in Gods mercy ye will do.</p>
               <p>§. 24. <hi>Pag.</hi> 24 25. But ye prove, That ye are not or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Schiſmaticks by three Reaſons: The firſt is, If ye be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:123874:32"/>Schiſmaticks, or culpable of Schiſme, <hi>Either it muſt relate,</hi> ſay you, <hi>to a differing from the former Eccleſiaſticall Government of this Church eſtabliſhed, and then who is not involved in it, as well as we? Or to that Conſtitution, and Government, that is yet to come; and untill that be agreed on, eſtabliſhed, and declared, and actually exiſt, there can be no guilt, or imputation of Schiſme from it:</hi> But none of theſe are true, as ye have confirmed it: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Howſoever I hold you not yet for Schiſmaticks; yet can I not think, that ye prove it well: For that diſ-junctive propoſition may be denyed, as not containing a full enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Cauſes, or Reaſons of Schiſme; for a Church may be Schiſmaticall, not onely for her Separation from this, or that Church, but much more for her Separation from all Churches, as your Accuſers may ſay of you, <hi>viz.</hi> That ye have quitted the Communion of all other Churches, as well Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, as Papiſts; and that in caſe ye could not, or would not joyn in union with Churches ruled by Epiſcopall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ye might have joyned your ſelves with other Reformed Churches, with which the Church of <hi>England</hi> entertained Union, and Communion; ſo that the greater your Separation was, the greater was your Schiſme. Yet can it not be ſaid, that it was a Schiſme <hi>formally,</hi> but <hi>materially,</hi> for it had not the <hi>eſſentiall forme,</hi> or that which we conceive, as the <hi>eſſentiall forme</hi> of a Schiſme, <hi>viz. Conviction, and Pertinacy,</hi> without the which <hi>Schiſme</hi> no more can be made up, then <hi>Hereſie:</hi> For it is <hi>Forma quae dat eſſe rei,</hi> the Forme that giveth being to a thing. Onely it had the <hi>matter,</hi> or <hi>materiall cauſe</hi> of a Schiſme, <hi>viz.</hi> The Separation from all Churches, which cannot make up a Schiſme <hi>formally,</hi> no more then a mans body alone, which is his matteriall cauſe, can <hi>formally</hi> make up a Man.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Men may yet be called Schiſmaticks, <hi>Materialiter &amp; Dispoſitivè, matterially,</hi> and <hi>dispoſitively,</hi> or <hi>as having the dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to Schiſme,</hi> when they cannot actually reſiſt an actuall Government, but are reſolved without any ſufficient cauſe to reſiſt, or controle that Government, that they judge, will be eſtabliſhed by them, who according to Gods ordinary Providence have power to do it. And ſo your Partie may yet
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:123874:33"/>ſay, that ye be culpable, and guiltie of Schiſme <hi>materially,</hi> and by way of <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> if they ſee you aym at any Toleration, which is the next way to Separation: So they may Anſwer unto the confirmations of both the parts of your diſ-junctive Propoſition in denying both your Aſſumptions; for many there be, who ſeparated not themſelves from all Proteſtant Churches, and that are not minded to oppoſe the forme of Government, that is to be eſtabliſhed, much leſſe to be ſuiters for Toleration.</p>
               <p>Your ſecond Reaſon to free your ſelves from the calumny of Schiſme, is this in ſubſtance. § 24. <hi>Pag.</hi> 24.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>If ye had been guided by the ſpirit of Schiſme, ye had made up a Partie, when ye had the occaſion.</item>
                  <item>But ſo did ye not, when ye had the occaſion: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Ye prove the connexion of your firſt Propoſition: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch are practiſes of thoſe, that are led by the ſpirit of Schiſme.</p>
               <p>Ye prove the Aſſumption. 1. Becauſe, that howſoever, ye <hi>had great provocations, viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Miſunderſtandings of your opinions.</hi> 2. <hi>Incitements to this State, not to allow you the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able practiſes of your conſciences, which the Reformed Churches abroad allowed you.</hi> 3. <hi>Calumnies in Print.</hi> 4. <hi>Heightned with this prejudice, that ye were aſhamed of your opinions, or able to ſay little for them.</hi> 5. <hi>Books printed againſt your opinions,</hi> yet ye did it not. 2. Becauſe, that having the occaſion of <hi>manifold ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to make, and increaſe a Partie,</hi> ye <hi>have not in the leaſt ſort attempted it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ye prove that ye had manifold advantages. 1. Becauſe <hi>ye found the ſpirits of the people of this Kingdom, that profeſſe or pretend to the power of godlineſſe, ready to take any impreſſions, and to be caſt in any mould, that hath but the appearance of a ſtricter way.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe that the miſts gathered about you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to ſcatter.</hi> 3. <hi>Becauſe ye publiſhed not your opinions by Preaching, although ye had the Pulpits free; nor in Print, although the Preſſes were more free, then the Pulpits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Your Partie will deny the Aſſumption; for if ye, and the reſt of your Partie made it not up, how is it made up in this Kingdom?</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:123874:33"/>
               <p>As for the proof of your Provocations: We have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered already to the firſt: The third and fourth, we allow it not, if any man hath done ſo. To the ſecond we ſhall anſwer hereafter. And as for the fifth, good Sheepherds could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an abominable prevarication, but write againſt yours, and all other mens <hi>Innovations,</hi> when they ſaw ſo many Sects mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, and Woolfs creeping in ſo faſt into Chriſts Sheep-fold, to devour the flock. 2. If ye blame our faithfull Miniſters for maintaining the Truth already received, what ſhall we ſay of your folks, who have firſt publiſhed Books againſt the Truth. 3. What ſhall we ſay of thoſe of your Colleagues, who heretofore preached your Tenets with great offence here in publike? And who ſtill run buſily up and down, to make Proſelytes.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond proof your Aſſumption.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. We have already anſwered, that it is made, but how we know not.</item>
                  <item>2. What were thoſe people that profeſſe, and pretend to any power of godlineſſe, ſo ready to take any impreſſion, and to make a Partie, ye tell not? We wiſh to know, whether they be Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, or of what other Sect?</item>
                  <item>3. Your Covenant obligeth you to declare it unto the Parliament however, ye reveal it not unto us.</item>
                  <item>4. Certainly true Profeſſors of godlineſſe are not ſo ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible of any impreſſions, much leſſe to become factious.</item>
                  <item>5. And therefore ye adde well <hi>(or pretend)</hi> for ſuch men <hi>pretend</hi> onely to <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> but have renounced <hi>(in effect)</hi> the <hi>power</hi> thereof.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Here we ſee, howſoever ye pretend not to be States-men, yet ye know as much of it as the Presbyterians.</p>
               <p>Your ſecond occaſion was the <hi>diſſipations of mists, &amp;c.</hi> If ſo, and onely ſo; then what needed this <hi>Apologeticall Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 25. <hi>Pag.</hi> 25. To the third occaſion, whether ye had the Pulpits ſo free, or feared to have them leſſe free afterwards, I diſpute not, ye know that well enough: Onely this I know, That ſome of your Brethren having given themſelves libertie to ſpeak ſomewhat freely in favour of your opinions, were
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:123874:34"/>afterwards diſcountenanced, and became more prudent, and circumſpect in venting of themſelves. If ye printed not your <hi>opinions,</hi> it may be, ye deal more prudently in teaching them in private, then in publiſhing them in Print. And here ye ſhew how your Charitie is grown cold; for in the beginning when ſo many <hi>miſts were gathered about you,</hi> for fear of Schiſme out of meet Charitie, ye abſtained from writing, and now, when they are <hi>ſcattered</hi> ye write.</p>
               <p>Your third Grievance is the reproach of that <hi>proud, and inſolent title of Independency.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Ye decline that proud Title, but will no wayes quit the thing ſignified by the Title, in that, ye maintain the <hi>Independency</hi> of every one of your Churches from all <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Authoritie,</hi> or <hi>Authoritative Power</hi> of any Eccleſiaſticall Aſſembly; yea, ſome of your Profeſſion ſay, That it belongs not to the Magiſtrate to puniſh any man for his Religion, be it never ſo odious, and wicked, as we have heard from their own mouths. So that there is <hi>another new Independency.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be replied here, That I did prove before, that ye ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſome Eccleſiaſticall Authoritie, whereunto your particular Churches are ſubject.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, It is but by neceſſary conſequence, that they muſt hold it, and not <hi>interminis,</hi> or <hi>expreſly</hi> that they beleeve it; for they deny <hi>interminis,</hi> what they muſt grant <hi>by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence:</hi> It is drawn out of the evaſions, that they bring againſt our Reaſons, whereby, whileſt they ſeek to eſcape, they are catcht.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. Your fourth Grievance, whereof ye complain, and bewall your ſelves, is <hi>Browniſme together with all their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> wherewith ye are traduced.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But ye diſclaim not <hi>Browniſme, and their Opinions,</hi> abſolutely, but with a reſtriction and <hi>ſecundum quid, viz. As they have ſtated, and maintained them.</hi> 2. By another limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi> That ye <hi>differ much from them,</hi> not <hi>in re, ſed in modo rei:</hi> It may be, ye hold, and maintain the ſame <hi>opinions,</hi> but not the <hi>ſame way.</hi> And yet ye ſympathize very much with them, in puining untoward names upon us, but not upon them.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:123874:34"/>
               <p>There alſo ye declare what ye <hi>confeſſe, and beleeve, viz. The trueth to lye in a middle way betwixt Browniſme, and the Authoritative Presbyteriall Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But this is nothing, but your errour: Veritie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in the middle of this, or that which ye imagine, but in a conformitie of our conceptions with their object, and due meaſure; which in this matter, is onely Gods Word revealed in the holy Scriptures; and according to this rule I take Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government, rather to be the middle betwixt <hi>Popiſh Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>Independent Anarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ 25. <hi>Pag.</hi> 25. Your fifth Grievance is <hi>Some incitements to this State, not to allow us</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>the peaceable practiſes of our Conſciences, which the Reformed Churches abroad allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If any man incited the State not to allow you a peaceable practiſe of your new Religion, they did according to their conſcience, as your <hi>New-England</hi> men do with thoſe of our Religion; and as ſome ſay, that ſome of you five would do with us.</p>
               <p>Their Reaſons might have been theſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe it cannot but open a door to all ſorts of erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Opinions.</item>
                  <item>2. It is dangerous for the State, it may breed factions and diviſions betwixt all perſons of whatſoever relation, betwixt the Magiſtrate, and the Subject, the Husband, and the Wife, the Father, and the Son, Brethren, Siſters, the Maſter, and the Servant; when the one is of one Religion, or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Government, and the other of another, as ye have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented: The Son may refuſe to receive any communion with the Father, and the Brother with the Brother, and ſo diſſolve all naturall, civill, and domeſticall bands of Societie.</item>
                  <item>3. No State in Chriſtendome, where there is one onely Religion eſtabliſhed, will admit the publike exerciſe of any other, or endure a Schiſme in that, which is already received: Wherefore then ſhould it be done here?</item>
                  <item>4. If it be granted to our Brethren, I cannot ſee how it can well be denyed to other Sects.</item>
               </list>
               <p>If it be ſaid, That other Sects differ more from us, then
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:123874:35"/>they do; it is all one, <hi>Magis &amp; minus non mutant Speciem,</hi> in matter of Toleration; for then all muſt be tolerated, howſoever ſome more, ſome leſſe: And ſome of our Brethren grant all the Argument: And if we diſtinguiſh ſo, ye muſt declare, and expound cleerly, what Sects, and what Opinions are to be tolerated, and what not, which will be a queſtion inextricable, which no mortall man, appearingly, is able diſtinctly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine.</p>
               <p>And ſome may ſay, The leſſe the difference be, the leſſe need is there for a Toleration to be granted to ſuch a Sect: For the leſſe it be, the greater is the Schiſme.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>5. God in the Old Teſtament granted no Toleration of divers Religions, or Diſciplines; and the New Teſtament re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth no leſſe union amongſt Chriſtians, then the old amongſt the Jews.</item>
                  <item>6. Either our Brethren do aſſent to our Doctrine, and are reſolved likewiſe to aſſent to the Diſcipline, which God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhall be eſtabliſhed by common conſent, or do not: If they grant the firſt, what need they any other Toleration, then the reſt? If the ſecond, it would be firſt diſcuſſed, wherein they are reſolved to diſſent; and afterwards conſidered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be of ſo great importance, that in conſideration thereof, they dare not, in good Conſcience, entertain communion with us.</item>
                  <item>7. They are not preſſed to be Actors in any thing againſt their Conſciences: <hi>Ergo,</hi> They need not to be ſuiters for a Toleration; or if they be, it may juſtly be refuſed.</item>
                  <item>8. It is againſt the nature of the Communion of Saints, to live in Sects apart, without communicating at the Lords Table, which very hardly will be avoided, if Toleration be granted.</item>
                  <item>9. Becauſe the Scripture exhorts us evermore unto unitie, which cannot be eaſily procured by a Toleration of Sects, which cannot but daily beget new Schiſmes and Diviſions.</item>
                  <item>10. Becauſe there was greater difference amongſt the Members of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> in the rim of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and yet they communicated together; yea, the Apoſtle exhorted
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:123874:35"/>them unto mutuall communion, and forbearance of Sects, and Diviſions.</item>
                  <item>11. Becauſe the Opinion of our Brethren ſymbolizeth too much with that of the Donatiſts, who ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from other Churches, under pretext, that they were not ſo holy as their own: Neither is it unlike to the Convents and Monaſteries amongſt the Papiſts; for as they all profeſſe one Doctrine with the Romiſh Church, and yet every Order hath its own Diſcipline; that of S. <hi>Francis</hi> one, that of S. <hi>Dominick</hi> another; and in every Order one Generall, and in every Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery one <hi>Abbot, Prior</hi> or Preſident; So all your Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve one Doctrine together with us, and every one of your Churches hath one Miniſter, as their Convents a particular <hi>Abbot</hi> or <hi>Prior.</hi> Ye onely differ in this, That ye have no Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or any thing anſwerable thereunto to keep you in unitie and conformitie.</item>
                  <item>12. It is the Civill Magiſtrates part to take away Hereſies, Superſtitions, and Corruptions in manners after the examples of the Kings of <hi>Juda:</hi> Wherefore then is not his dutie like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to take away all Schiſmes, which are the high-way to Hereſie, and conſequently to deny Toleration, which is a way to both.</item>
                  <item>13. We have but one God, one Chriſt, and one Lord, one Spirit, we are one Body, we have one Faith, and one Baptiſm, whereby we enter into the Church: Wherefore ſhall we not have one Communion, whereby to be ſpiritually fed, and one Diſcipline to be ruled by?</item>
                  <item>14. If Churches have Diſciplines, or Governments dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in their <hi>Species,</hi> then the Churches muſt be different in their <hi>Species</hi> alſo; for all Collective bodies, or Conſociations that are governed, are differenced by their different Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as we ſee in Civill Government, in the Conſtitution, and Diſtinction of States, Kingdoms, and Republikes: Wherefore as many divers Governments, as there be in Churches, as many different <hi>Species</hi> of Churches muſt we admit of, I ſpeak here of the Church conſidered according to her viſible forme, but the conſequent is falſe, ſince there is but one Church. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:123874:36"/>
                  <item>15. Neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles, ever granted any Toleration to divers Sects and Governments in the Church; wherefore then will ye be Suiters for that, which they never granted?</item>
                  <item>16. Yea, your <hi>New-England</hi> men (<hi>whoſe wayes and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Government</hi> (ye ſay) <hi>are improved to a better Edition, and greater refinement,</hi> whom ye compare with our Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Pag.</hi> 5. tolerated not their Brethren, who did hazard their lives in that voyage, but made them go again, as our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſeek out ſome new Habitations in ſtrange Countreyes, yea, in ſtrange <hi>Wilderneſſes,</hi> for themſelves, and their ſeed after them; yea, they would not ſo much as ſome very godly and learned Divine relateth in his learned Book againſt Toleration) as receive ſome men, otherwiſe approved by themſelves, both for their life and Doctrine, to live in any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>New-England,</hi> howſoever here they were in danger to be perſecuted for Non-conformitie; And that mee ly, becauſe they differed a little from them in point of Diſcipline. How then can our Brethren of that profeſſion be Suiters for a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Old <hi>England,</hi> where they are no more perſecuted, when as thoſe of their profeſſion refuſed it to thoſe of <hi>New-England</hi> in time of great perſecution? Is it not to be feared, That if they had the upper hand over us here, as there, they ſhould ſend us all to ſome Iſle of Dogs, as they have done others?</item>
                  <item>17. Beſides all this, the Scripture forbiddeth all ſuch To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration,<note place="margin">Reve. 2 20 1 Cor 1.12.</note> as that of <hi>Jezabel;</hi> There muſt be no ſuch ſpeeches amongſt us, <hi>as I am of Paul, I of Apollos, I of Cephas;</hi> nor that ſome are <hi>Calvinians,</hi> as ye terme us, ſome <hi>Independenters,</hi> ſome <hi>Browniſts,</hi> ſome <hi>Anabaptiſts, &amp;c.</hi> We muſt all be <hi>Chriſts,</hi> we muſt all think, and ſpeak the ſame things, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe men are carnall:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3. 1 Cor. 11.16, 18, 19, 20. Heb 10.25. Gal. 5.12.</note> Neither hath the Church of God a cuſtome to be contentious: Neither permitteth the Apoſtle Schiſmes: We muſt not quit our mutuall meetings, as others do, and as muſt be done in a publike Toleration. They that trouble the Church muſt be cut off.</item>
                  <item>18. Such a Toleration cannot but expoſe our Churches unto the calumnies of Papiſts, who evermore object unto
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:123874:36"/>Proteſtants the innumerable number of their Sects, whereas they pretend to be nothing but one Church.</item>
                  <item>19. Of ſuch a Toleration follows all we formerly dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of <hi>Independency.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>20. If it be granted, it cannot but be thought, that it hath been granted, or rather extorted by force of Reaſon, and that all the Aſſembly were not able to anſwer our Brethrens, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed their Opinion, and Demands are againſt all Reaſon, as ſundry of themſelves could not deny, and had nothing to ſay, ſave onely that it was Gods Ordinance, which yet they never could ſhew out of Gods Word: On the contrary, if it be refuſed, it will help to confirm the Churches, and the people in the Truth.</item>
                  <item>21. Neither can it but overthrow all ſort of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Government; for a man being cenſured in one Church, may fly to another; and being again ſuſpended in that other, from thence to another, and ſo ſcorn all the Churches of God, and their Cenſures; And ſo this order by neceſſary conſequence will breed all ſort of diſorder.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I omit here many other Reaſons, taken
<list>
                     <item>1. From the <hi>Efficient cauſe</hi> of Toleration, as they who can permit, or Tolerate Shiſmes: Whether mortal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> men have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any power of God, either <hi>jure divino,</hi> or <hi>naturally</hi> to diſpence with Gods Ordinances, and to permit that which he forbiddeth.</item>
                     <item>2. From the <hi>object</hi> of it, <hi>viz.</hi> If it be good, or ill, for ſuch as the <hi>object</hi> is, ſuch muſt the Toleration, or permiſſion <hi>be.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. From the <hi>Forme, viz.</hi> If it be conſonant unto Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or not. For if it be not, it muſt be ill, ſince Scripture muſt be the rule of all acts of Chriſtian duties.</item>
                     <item>4. From the <hi>End,</hi> for if the <hi>End</hi> be ill, it is ill; yea, howſoever it be good, yet is it not good to permit ill for a good <hi>end,</hi> as the Apoſtle teacheth us; for howſoever God may do it, yet cannot we do it; For he who did draw light out of darkneſſe, can draw, good out of ſin yea, more good out of ſin, then is the ill that it containeth in it ſelf; So cannot we.</item>
                     <item>5. From the <hi>Obligation that lieth upon us, to do all the good we can:</hi> and conſequently, not onely to forbear ſin our ſelves,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:123874:37"/>but alſo to hinder others from ſin, ſince it ſtriketh at Gods honour, which we are bound to maintain againſt all men.</item>
                     <item>6. From the <hi>Obligation, that lieth upon us,</hi> not to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers in other mens <hi>ſins, in approving,</hi> or not <hi>hindering them</hi> in, ſo far forth as lieth in us; For the power of hindering ſin, is not given us for nothing, but for its End, which is its Act, <hi>viz.</hi> To hinder it actually.</item>
                     <item>7. From the <hi>Obſtatles;</hi> For God hath dealt ſo mercifully with the tate here, that there is no Force greater then it ſelf, to compell it, to permit, or tolerate many Sects, Shiſmes, or Hereſies; So that the fewer the Obſtacles be found, the greater will the ſin of a Toleration be found: But we fear to be to long upon this point.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Your ſixth Grievance, <hi>Our ſilence was interpreted, that we were either aſhamed of our Opinions, or able to ſay little for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If any man hath uttered any ſuch expreſſions out of malice, or contempt of your Perſons, they are to be blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: If out of zeal to the Trueth, and of the good Opinion they have of you, I beleeve ye will not blame them; for all good men eſteem you to be very godly men, and no men of learning know you; but they know you to be very learned men, as ſome of your Books teſtifie aboundantly: But if little can be ſaid to the purpoſe, for that cauſe which ye main tain, what marvell is it, That ye can ſay little for it? Neither can honeſt men doubt, but an ill man can and will ſay more for it, then all ye ſive can ſay, ſo ſoon as ye have conſidered it more profoundly: And the better men ye be, the leſſe ye will have to ſay. Ye are not ſo able to maintain an ill cauſe, as an ill man.</p>
               <p>Your ſeventh Grievance. <hi>Books have been written</hi> (ſay ye again) <hi>to prepoſſeſſe againſt what are preſuppoſed our Tenets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not what are your five Teners, but of thoſe who have written upon that Subject; If yours be different from theirs, ſo ſoon as ye ſhall cleerly declare them, they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an anſwer; And therefore it was nor to <hi>prepoſſeſſe</hi> them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to keep them in <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of the <hi>truth</hi> already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:123874:37"/>
               <p>Afterwards ye give Reaſons of your ſilence. 1. <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>it is the ſecond blow, that makes the quarrell, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. We are aſſured that ye have given the firſt, ſecond, and third blow, as it may eaſily appear by your Books, and Sermons here at <hi>London,</hi> as we have already anſwered. For the Books of the Divines that wrote againſt your Opinions, were onely Anſwers unto Arguments of thoſe of your Partie. So then ye have made the quarrell. 2. This Reaſon, as it hindered you in the beginning, ſo ſhould it at this preſent.</p>
               <p>Your ſecond Reaſon is, <hi>Your conſcientious apprebenſion of the danger of rending the godly Proteſtant Party.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Wherefore then did it not hinder you from Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this <hi>Apologeticall Narration?</hi> as we ſaid before.</p>
               <p>Your third Reaſon is, <hi>The conjurements of many Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, Wiſe, and godly Perſonages of both the Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If their Conjurements have ſo long been ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all with you, how have they been now of late ſo inefficacious, that they could not hinder the Printing of this Book? How augment ye now this <hi>unhappy difference?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Reaſon. The <hi>Declarations of the Parliament about the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Proteſtants againſt Popery, their reſpect to tender Conſciences, as might prevent oppreſſions which had formerly been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Your Covenant. 6. And your duely reſpect to a peaceable Reformation. To theſe three, I anſwer as unto the third.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>The hopefull expectation of an happy latitude, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The agreement may be happy, if ye will, and ſo ye may obtain what ye might hopefully expect. 1. For I hope ye ſhall be freed from all oppreſſions, like to thoſe ye formerly ſuffered under. 2. That ye may poſſeſſe your Conſciences in place. 3. That ye ſhall not be compelled to any externall Confeſſion, contrary to your preſent Tenets. 4. Much leſſe to be Actors in any thing againſt your Conſcience. And thus farre your <hi>hopefull expectation</hi> might have been well grounded. But if ye <hi>expected</hi> a <hi>Toleration</hi> for all Sects, or that we ſhould
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:123874:38"/>have received your Opinions, ye hoped more, then ye had ground for.</p>
               <p>Now, whereas in the two laſt lines, ye <hi>ſubmit this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of your judgement, to the due, and orderly agitation of this Aſſembly; whereof</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>both Houſes were pleaſed to make us Members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reader will do well to conſider how cautiouſly ye ſpeak here. 1. <hi>Ye ſubmit this Declaration of your judgement, not to the judgement of the Aſſembly,</hi> as if the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſhould be ſubject unto Prophets; But onely to the <hi>Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Aſſembly,</hi> and ſo ye ſeem no wayes minded to ſubmit your ſelves unto the <hi>Aſſemblies judgement,</hi> as all the reſt of the Members thereof, and of this Church too. 2. Neither ſubmit ye it ſimply to the <hi>Agitation,</hi> but to the <hi>due and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Agitation of this Aſſembly,</hi> as if before ye had obſerved ſome undue; or unorderly <hi>Agitation</hi> of buſineſſe in it, or feared it hereafter.</p>
               <p>Truely this undue reſtriction might very well have been omitted, for it is holden for a certain and undoubted Maxime amongſt all Proteſtants, That the Church has no abſolute power in her Judgements; That ſhe cannot obliege us to do any ill; And that we are not bound to obey her unjuſt Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and Commands; But that it is better to obey God, then men.</p>
               <p>This Submiſſion is very feriall, and worthy to be preſented to ſome idle fellows: Ye will permit the Aſſembly from Morning till Evening to agitate, and diſpute your Opinions, as if they had no other thing to do, neither here, or at home; A great <hi>ſubmiſſion,</hi> indeed of your <hi>judgements,</hi> which ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not refuſe to the ordinarieſt Mechanick in the World; for ſince it is <hi>publiei juris</hi> publiſhed, they will aſſubject your judgement unto theirs, by way of <hi>Agitation,</hi> or diſputing of it amongſt themſelves, as much as all the Divines of <hi>England,</hi> yea, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye will or not.</p>
               <p>Again, Since both Houſes were pleaſed to make you <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of that <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> was not that a ſufficient Juſtification, and Vindication of your Perſons from all <hi>calumnies ſpread againſt you,</hi> and already <hi>ſcattered without ſpeaking a word for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:123874:38"/>your ſelves?</hi> § 24. <hi>Pag.</hi> 24. Truely it is to be ſuppoſed, that the two Houſes would never recommend men thither, either ignorant, or vicious, but the learnedeſt, and godlieſt of the Kingdom; ſo this your Apology is unſeaſonable: Onely this needs an Apology, That being Members of the Aſſembly, ye will not ſubmit your ſelves unto the Aſſembly of Divines, but take odde wayes, proper to you five alone, to publiſh parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Apologies, and deſire a particular Toleration, which no other Members of the Aſſembly do. But as for this, <hi>tranſeat cum coeteris crroribus.</hi> It ſufficeth that ye ſee extraordinary teſtimonies of the Parliaments, and Aſſemblies moſt tender affection towards you; how they have tolerated much in you, the like whereof hath not yet been tolerated in any Member, either of Parliament, or of the Aſſembly; and all to the end, to chaſe away all pannick fears from your mindes, and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>diſadvantages,</hi> which ye <hi>did forcſee,</hi> § 26.</p>
               <p>§ 26. <hi>Pag.</hi> 28. Howſoever ye commend much the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and declare, That <hi>ye grant more to the Civill Magiſtrate, then the principles of Presbyteriall Government will ſuffer them to yeeld;</hi> Yet even here ye rap him over the Knuckles, as if in making you Members of the Aſſembly, he ſhould have been partiall, in placing you there with ſo many <hi>diſadvantages;</hi> yea (as ye ſay) <hi>And therein alſo upon all ſorts of diſadvantages, which we could not but foreſee, both in number, abilities of learning, Authoritie, the ſtream of publike intereſt, Truſting God both with our ſelves, and his own Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I maintain that the Parliament has done you no wrong, for ye were not forced to ſit there; If there be ſo great diſadvantages, ye might have choſen, whether you would have ſit there at all, or not. All rationall men think it a great favour, which ye eſteem ſo great a <hi>diſadvantage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the Number. 1. Think ye that the Parliament ought to have put in ſuch a Number of you, that agree not in your opinions amongſt your ſelves, as might have over-ſwayed all the Divines of the Kingdom, to the end that ye might after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward have compelled us all to quit the Kingdom, as your Friends of <hi>New-England</hi> have done to others? 2. Were ye to be compared in <hi>number</hi> with the reſt of the Divines in this
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:123874:39"/>Kingdom, who are hundreds for one of you? Juſtice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in an <hi>Arithmeticall,</hi> but in a <hi>Geometricall proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which here has been obſerved towards you; and that with more equitie then Juſtice. 3. Neither did the Parliament hinder you, to call as many Divines of your Profeſſion, as pleaſed you to conſult with apart. 4. Neither need ye ſo great a <hi>number</hi> in the Aſſemblie; for ye ſeem not (for any thing we can ſee) reſolved to ſubmit your ſelves, or to acquieſſe with any pluralitie of voices, either of Parliament, or Aſſemblie; wherefore then deſire ye ſo great a <hi>number?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for Abilities in Learning. 1. Ye might alſo have had with you, if it had pleaſed you, as many learned men as ye could finde. 2. Neither beleeve I, that any others of your Profeſſion could prudently take ſuch a buſineſſe in hand without you: Who ever knows you, knows well ye want no abilities to diſpute your opinion in any Aſſemblie in <hi>Europe:</hi> Men of learning, and of wiſedome therefore think, that you ſpeak this rather out of modeſtie, then otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>What ye underſtand by <hi>Authoritie,</hi> I know not; it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Eccleſiaſticall, ſince ye acknowledge none in the Church: Then it muſt be politicall, and namelie, that of the King, and Parliament, ſince that no other at this preſent, have power over you; and then I could wiſh, ye had ſpoken more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Publike intereſt,</hi> Either this muſt be taken of <hi>publike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in <hi>Religion;</hi> and then it 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, or ſhould be our ſole aym; and it is no <hi>diſadvantage</hi> for you, That both the Parliament, and the Aſſemblie, be led by this <hi>Intereſt:</hi> Or <hi>in State,</hi> and then ye wrong both the Parliament, and the Aſſemblie, as if they meaſured Religion by Worldlie <hi>Ends,</hi> and <hi>Intereſts,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in ye are not to be beleeved. Neither will we retaliate unto you, that you may have ſome further <hi>Intereſts</hi> yet, that we know not of.</p>
               <p>And conſequentlie ye need not to fear for your Perſons, as if ye were in danger, or had ſubject to fear perſecution, as in former time.</p>
               <p>§ 27. <hi>Pag.</hi> 28. Ye excuſe your ſelves from falſe Doctrine, whereof no man accuſeth you.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:123874:39"/>
               <p>§ 28. Ye tell us, that the Difference betwixt you, and us, is not ſo great; the leſſe it is, the leſſe ſhould ye be ſuiters for a Toleration; and if ye obtained it, the greater ſhould be your Schiſme.</p>
               <p>§ 28. <hi>Pag.</hi> 30. Here alſo ye excuſe your ſelves, that ye have not made a Scholaſtique Relation of your Judgement, whereunto we have already anſwered; and in ſo doing your opinions remaining leſſe known, hardly can they be diſtinctlie refuted.</p>
               <p>§ 28. <hi>Pag.</hi> 39, 30. Afterwards ye require two things of the <hi>Parliament, That it will look upon you under no other Notion, or Character, then as thoſe, who do as little differ from the Reformed Churches,</hi> and your Brethren; yea, far leſſe, then they do from what themſelves were three yeers paſt, or then the generalitie of this Kingdom from it ſelf of late. 2. Ye require <hi>an allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a latitude to ſome leſſer differences with peaceableneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And we pray you, do, as they have done, to the end, the Parliament may look upon you, as they do upon them. 1. They never condemned all the Proteſtant Churches, as ye do. 2. They never deſired a Toleration, to make a Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as ye do. 3. Either they approved not the ill of the times paſt, but patientlie endured it according to their light, hoping and praying to God for better, without Schiſme. 4. Or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it: but when it pleaſed God in his mercy to illuminate them, they diſapproved what before they had approved of, and changed from worſe to better; which if ye do, O what a joy ſhall it be unto them, and to us all, and what a content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may it bring unto your ſelves?</p>
               <p>And finally, As for the <hi>latitude</hi> and <hi>tolerance</hi> ye ſue for, it is unjuſt, and moſt pernicious, both to Chriſts Church, and the Kingdom, as we have hear already cleerly demonſtrated.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
